<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://hengzhubao.github.io/</id>
    <title>求是法道Hengzhu Bao</title>
    <updated>2020-11-20T10:18:09.465Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://hengzhubao.github.io/"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://hengzhubao.github.io/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>Nothing in my mind except nothing!</subtitle>
    <logo>https://hengzhubao.github.io/images/avatar.png</logo>
    <icon>https://hengzhubao.github.io/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2020, 求是法道Hengzhu Bao</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Experimental investigations of three laser-induced synchronized bubbles]]></title>
        <id>https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/manuscript1/</id>
        <link href="https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/manuscript1/">
        </link>
        <updated>2020-11-19T17:07:15.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105375">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105375</a></p>
<h1 id="abstract">Abstract</h1>
<p>Herein, we investigated experimentally the dynamics of three laser-induced, same-sized, symmetrically aligned, and synchronized bubbles. Three synchronized laser beams split from the same beam using a Diffractive Optical Element splitter were focused on water, and then we obtained three bubbles. Another nanosecond laser pulse was used to probe the bubbles to obtain shadowgraphs. The exact delay of the excited and detected light was controlled using a delay generator. The results revealed that the maximum volumes of bubbles in arrays decrease as the normalized distance falls, while the lifetimes and translation increase. It was explained by the interaction between the acoustic radiation of bubbles and the surrounding bubbles. The shrinkage of linear bubble arrays exists an anomaly. The center bubbles were stretched, to ellipsoid, stick, even fractured, by the peripheral bubbles. The closer they are, the more distinct is the above phenomenon. However, when the normalized distance was sufficiently small, instead of being stretched, the center bubbles were compressed to disk shape and thus shrank with the whole array. Finally, the dependence of the distance on the energy transfer of the bubble system is also discussed.<br>
Keywords: Multi-bubbles dynamics, Laser-induced bubbles, Linear arrays, Non-spherical bubble, Holographic generation of bubbles</p>
<h1 id="i-introduction">I. Introduction</h1>
<p>Cavitation is an important phase-transition phenomenon in many fields, such as acoustics, sonochemistry, medicine, and hydraulics[1–8]. In the practice of these fields, cavitation is not isolated single one but tends to appear as filaments, streamers, clusters, and clouds in different styles of multiple bubbles groups. Studies on cavitation mainly focus on the deformation and mechanics revealed in the bubble dynamics and also the primary parameters of which are the phase and the size of bubbles. In a tiny region of the bubble groups, every two adjacent bubbles usually have similar phases and sizes [1,9,10]. In this respect, it is thus critical to clarify the interaction among the same-sized and synchronized multiple bubbles.</p>
<p>Many previous studies have focused on a single bubble, which assumes that the individual bubble behaviors are independent of the groups. The dynamics of a single bubble has been studied extensively for many years. For instance, Rayleigh, Plesset, Gilmore, and Keller studied the aspects of a single spherical bubble and developed the corresponding mathematical models[11–18]. On the other hand, in the studies of bubble groups, it was assumed that all bubbles followed the Rayleigh-Plesset model. In this case, these bubbles oscillate with the driving acoustic fields. Moreover, the natural frequency of bubble groups is lower than that of a single bubble. In the center of bubble groups, there exists energy accumulation and radiates high-intensity noise. When generated near the rigid boundary, bubble groups keep stationary for a while and then move toward the rigid boundary[7,18–27].</p>
<p>In fact, each bubble in the bubble groups is not independent. Thus the investigations on the interaction between two bubbles are significant because such studies can provide a valuable basis for multiple bubbles. Shima, Prosperetti, Mettin, Harkin, Fujikawa, Lauternborn, B.C.Khoo, Ohl explored two bubbles experimentally and theoretically based on the hypothesis of bubbles keeping spherical[28–37]. Consequently, it was noted that two synchronized bubbles with similar sizes usually attract each other and form jets towards each other in their shrink phase, and they have a longer lifetime. Nonetheless, when bubble pairs only have one pair of interactions, while bubbles in groups usually have several adjacent bubbles to interact with. Furthermore, the exact mechanism of interaction among multiple (i.e., three or more ) bubbles remains elusive[1,38]. However, the studies of bubble arrays have partially solved this problem.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, J.P.Dear and J.E.Field created static tension bubbles in gelatin, to study the reaction of acoustic pulse on the bubble arrays[39,40]. Nicolas Bremond, Manish Arora, Claus-Dieter Ohl, and Detlef Lohse studied the interaction of inflatable bubble arrays generated from a rigid surface[41,42]. Quinto-Su, Claus-Dieter Ohl focused laser modified by a spatial light modulator(SLM) on a liquid gap clamped by glass slides, to obtain quasi-two-dimensional bubble arrays. The studies indicated that, for a specific bubble, its adjacent bubbles modify its ambient pressure, and thereby mutually screen the pressure from the further position at the direction of the adjacent bubble[40,43]. The inner bubbles are confined by adjacent bubbles in the array dimensions. Their dynamics are primarily controlled by the reaction of adjacent bubbles and the free dimension. On the other hand, the peripheral bubbles are minimally confined, and their lifetimes are close to the isolated single bubble. Hence, the bubbles located centrally live most. Then the arrays collapse with a time sequence from outer to inner.</p>
<p>In general, three bubbles should receive more attention due to their high observability caused by a little amount, and high representativeness of mutual interaction from multiple adjacent bubbles. Siew -Wan Ohl, Lup Wai Chew, B.C.Khoo, and A.M.Zhang studied the dynamics of arrays of three bubbles generated by electric sparks in the free domain[34,36,44]. When the distances between synchronized bubbles are large, the center bubble will split when collapse, and each part will join with the verge bubbles, whereas three bubbles will join directly in the small distance case. The generated time and size influence the direction and style of bubble collapse. However, they did not control the position and energy of the exciting sources orderly. The dependence of separate distance on the orderly arranged arrays of similar bubbles has yet to be fully revealed.</p>
<p>In this paper, the holographic generation of millimeter-sized bubbles in a three-dimensional water column is attained using a high-power laser with a splitter. We used three split laser beams to accurately generate synchronized bubbles, with strictly controlled initial phases and size. Herein we purposed to clarify the dynamics of linear arrays of same-sized and synchronized cavitation bubbles in a quasi-free domain. Note that this paper concentrates on the deformation, size, lifetime, and translation of three synchronized bubbles in uniform alignment at different separate distances, during the period from birth to collapse, of laser-induced cavitation bubbles, which differs from the investigations above. Our approach is suitable for 3D geometries and a rather high laser fluence, which previously were not available. Such a study is currently lacking, and thus there is an urgent need for this aspect to be probed.</p>
<p>This paper is structured as follows. The second chapter introduces the experimental arrangement and the parameters of measurement. Relevant experimental results are presented in Chapter 3. In this chapter, the dynamics of multiple bubbles in the first oscillation period are analyzed. Then in a new chapter, some further discussions on the experiments are stated. Finally, minimum conclusions are provided.</p>
<h1 id="ii-experimental-setup">II. Experimental setup</h1>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="1"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr1.jpg" alt="fig1" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 1. Experimental arrangement for shadowgraphy of laser-induced multiple cavitation bubbles.</p>
<p>The experimental arrangement employed in this study for investigating the dynamics of laser-induced three symmetrically aligned in-phase bubbles is depicted in Figure 1.</p>
<p>To generate cavitation bubbles, a pulsed Nd:YAG laser generator (wavelength:1064nm; maximum energy:1J; pulse duration:10ns) was employed. The single laser pulse energy ranges from 100mJ to 1J. The fluctuations of the laser energy are approximately ±5%. Additionally, a beam splitter was utilized to split the pulse into two parts. Of which one part was reflected in an energy meter to monitor the incident pulse energy, while the other part was modulated into three beams using a triple-spot splitter DOE (Diffractive Optical Element; Holo/Or TS-245-I-Y-A). These three beams were aligned in the same vertical plane. Three mirrors were utilized to reflect these beams to an aplanat (f =30mm). The three reflecting spots aligned in the intersection of the incident plane, and also the plane in which the reflected laser and alignment bubbles were. Afterward, the aplanat lens was used for focusing on smaller spots to obtain regular bubbles. Hence, three pulse beams were focused and aligned on the focal plane. At these three focal points, deionized water was broken down in the water tank (fused silica, 50mm* 50mm * 50mm). Furthermore, plasma was generated, which then evolved into bubbles. We can obtain one or two bubbles by blocking certain beams. During the experiments, we set the different angles of the three incident beams, and the different distance between the mirrors to get different distances of the foci.</p>
<p>To visualize the fast process of bubble oscillation, we used a single frame CCD(Imi,imc7017g) combined with a short duration laser (Nd:YAG, wavelength = 1064nm, pulse duration = 2.5 ns). The probe laser propagates through the KTP frequency doubling crystal, and then the 1064nm pulse is transformed into a 532nm pulse. The new probe pulse beam was decayed and expanded through the aperture and the collimating expanding lens system. Afterward, the pulse beam which carries the information of bubbles propagates in the water and then approaching the CCD camera. The detection light was perpendicular to the exciting laser and the bubble line. A delay generator (Stanford Research Systems Inc., DG535) was utilized to trigger the CCD camera and lasers. By reading the time delay between the plasma flash and probe pulse, which was detected by a photodiode, we obtained the exact time of the image which was gathered using the CCD.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="2"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr2.jpg" alt="fig2" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 2. A schematic description of the bubble setups, including the definitions of several essential parameters. The left upper frame shows the maximum radius of an isolated single bubble. The red dash is an outline circle. The shadow area can be used to calculate the radius, which is obtained by the collapse time with the K-M model. The left lower frame shows the initial breakdown spots when γ=0.45. The mean value of the yellow and green length is the initial distance of bubbles, D0. The right frame is a typical image in γ=0.8. The red dash is the minimum bounding rectangle of the verge bubbles, whereas, the blue one is the minimum bounding rectangle of the center bubble. The green line is the B-verge-outer, while the yellow line is B-verge-inner. The pale blue line is the minor axis of the center bubble, B-center, while the orange line is the major axes, and also it can be defined as 2*A in different bubbles. D refers to the exact distance that is not shown in the scheme. It is a mean value of the distance of the centroids, which are the intersection points of the three cross in the frame.</p>
<p>Here, parameters that we focused on include the size and distance of bubbles. The radii of bubbles at a specific time, R, are obtained by the shadows, whose area is πR2. Given is the maximum radius of bubbles R0 in a single oscillation process. The initial distance D0 is the mean value of the distances between each two adjacent breakdown spots, as depicted in Figure 2. For normalization, a dimensionless parameter γ is defined as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>γ</mi><mo>=</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>D</mi><mn>0</mn></msub><mrow><mn>2</mn><msub><mi>R</mi><mn>0</mn></msub></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\gamma = \frac { D _ { 0 } } { 2 R _ { 0 } }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.625em;vertical-align:-0.19444em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.05556em;">γ</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.3335309999999998em;vertical-align:-0.44509999999999994em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8884309999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.655em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:-0.00773em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">0</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.4101em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:-0.02778em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">0</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.44509999999999994em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span><br>
(1.1)</p>
<p>Other important parameters in the bubble dynamics A, B are shown in Figure 2. Because of the interaction between bubbles, they lose their sphericities during the oscillation. Considering two-dimensional patterns, A is the semi-major axis of the bubble in the photos, while B is the semi-minor axis. However, the profile of the bubble is usually irregular. We treat the horizontal axis of the minimum bounding rectangle as the major axis of the bubble. Moreover, the distance from the centroid to the outer horizontal side of the rectangle is defined as B-outer, so does the B-inner. Two verge/peripheral bubbles average a general A, B-outer, and B-inner. Furthermore, B of the center bubble is the average of the distances from the centroid to the top and bottom.</p>
<p>To understand the deformation in the whole process, a normalized parameter C, that is, the degree of circularity is introduced[45]. It is defined as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>C</mi><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>m</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>t</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>o</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>a</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>a</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>e</mi><mi>q</mi><mi>u</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>v</mi><mi>a</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>t</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>c</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>c</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>e</mi></mrow><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>m</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>t</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>o</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>b</mi><mi>u</mi><mi>b</mi><mi>b</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>e</mi></mrow></mfrac><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mrow><mn>2</mn><msqrt><mrow><mi>π</mi><mi>S</mi></mrow></msqrt></mrow><msub><mi>P</mi><mi>b</mi></msub></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">C=\frac {perimeter-of-area-equivalent-circle }{perimeter-of-bubble} =\frac { 2 \sqrt { \pi S } } { P _ { b } }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.68333em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4133239999999998em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322159999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">m</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">o</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.10764em;">f</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">u</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.01968em;">l</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">m</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">o</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.10764em;">f</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">q</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">u</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">v</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.01968em;">l</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">n</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.01968em;">l</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4974629999999998em;vertical-align:-0.4508599999999999em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.046603em;"><span style="top:-2.655em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">P</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.3448em;"><span style="top:-2.3487714285714287em;margin-left:-0.13889em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.15122857142857138em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span><span class="mord sqrt mtight"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322900000000001em;"><span class="svg-align" style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord mtight" style="padding-left:0.833em;"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">π</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.05764em;">S</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.89229em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="hide-tail mtight" style="min-width:0.853em;height:1.08em;"><svg width='400em' height='1.08em' viewBox='0 0 400000 1080' preserveAspectRatio='xMinYMin slice'><path d='M95,702c-2.7,0,-7.17,-2.7,-13.5,-8c-5.8,-5.3,-9.5,
-10,-9.5,-14c0,-2,0.3,-3.3,1,-4c1.3,-2.7,23.83,-20.7,67.5,-54c44.2,-33.3,65.8,
-50.3,66.5,-51c1.3,-1.3,3,-2,5,-2c4.7,0,8.7,3.3,12,10s173,378,173,378c0.7,0,
35.3,-71,104,-213c68.7,-142,137.5,-285,206.5,-429c69,-144,104.5,-217.7,106.5,
-221c5.3,-9.3,12,-14,20,-14H400000v40H845.2724s-225.272,467,-225.272,467
s-235,486,-235,486c-2.7,4.7,-9,7,-19,7c-6,0,-10,-1,-12,-3s-194,-422,-194,-422
s-65,47,-65,47z M834 80H400000v40H845z'/></svg></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.10770999999999997em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.4508599999999999em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span><br>
(1.2)</p>
<p>where S denotes the area of the bubble in the photos, which has a perimeter Pb. The numerator of this equation means the perimeter or circumference of a circle, which has an area equal to that of a bubble with perimeter Pb. In this case, a perfect circle has a C= 1. The more the bubble shape varies from being a circle, the smaller the circularity value.</p>
<p>To track the relative location changing of bubbles, a non-dimensional distance   is introduced. It is defined as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><msup><mi>D</mi><mo mathvariant="normal">′</mo></msup><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mi>D</mi><msub><mi>D</mi><mn>0</mn></msub></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">{D&#x27;}=\frac {D}{D_0}</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.751892em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.751892em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">′</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.317431em;vertical-align:-0.44509999999999994em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.872331em;"><span style="top:-2.655em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:-0.02778em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight">0</span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.44509999999999994em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span>(1.3)</p>
<p>where D represents the distance in a certain time, while D0 represents the initial distance between the verge bubbles to the center bubble as introduced in Figure 2.</p>
<p>In these experiments, the maximum bubble radii were obtained in single spherical bubble experiments in the bulk of water before the bubble arrays experiments with the same laser energy [33,34]. We recorded the oscillation of single bubbles in bulk water as well as measured their collapse time. The results of this experiment concurred with the radius in the Keller-Miksis model. The time of collapse the photos recorded fluctuated about ±5%. Thus, the ideal maximum radius of a single oscillating bubble in bulk water with a notation R0 is characterized by the mid-value of collapse time [46]. Compared with the results from the area of shadows in the shadowgraph, which is <span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mo>(</mo><msqrt><mrow><mi>max</mi><mo>⁡</mo><mo>(</mo><mtext>Area</mtext><mo>)</mo></mrow></msqrt><mo>)</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">/</mi><mi>π</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">( \sqrt { \max ( \text {Area} ) } ) / \pi</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.24em;vertical-align:-0.30499999999999994em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord sqrt"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.935em;"><span class="svg-align" style="top:-3.2em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3.2em;"></span><span class="mord" style="padding-left:1em;"><span class="mop">max</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord text"><span class="mord">Area</span></span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.8950000000000005em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3.2em;"></span><span class="hide-tail" style="min-width:1.02em;height:1.28em;"><svg width='400em' height='1.28em' viewBox='0 0 400000 1296' preserveAspectRatio='xMinYMin slice'><path d='M263,681c0.7,0,18,39.7,52,119c34,79.3,68.167,
158.7,102.5,238c34.3,79.3,51.8,119.3,52.5,120c340,-704.7,510.7,-1060.3,512,-1067
c4.7,-7.3,11,-11,19,-11H40000v40H1012.3s-271.3,567,-271.3,567c-38.7,80.7,-84,
175,-136,283c-52,108,-89.167,185.3,-111.5,232c-22.3,46.7,-33.8,70.3,-34.5,71
c-4.7,4.7,-12.3,7,-23,7s-12,-1,-12,-1s-109,-253,-109,-253c-72.7,-168,-109.3,
-252,-110,-252c-10.7,8,-22,16.7,-34,26c-22,17.3,-33.3,26,-34,26s-26,-26,-26,-26
s76,-59,76,-59s76,-60,76,-60z M1001 80H40000v40H1012z'/></svg></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.30499999999999994em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord">/</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">π</span></span></span></span> , small differences can be ignored. The initial distance of bubbles, D0, was extracted by the earliest frame below 100ns, while plasma is recombining and converting to vapor[47].</p>
<p>Keller-Miksis(K-M) model is a relatively complete model, describing the oscillation of single spherical bubbles. It takes into account the surface tension, viscosity, compressibility and gas inside the bubble[17], reading</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mi>R</mi><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>¨</mo></mover><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><msup><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mrow><mn>3</mn><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mi>ρ</mi></mfrac><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mi>R</mi><mrow><mi>ρ</mi><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mfrac><mrow><mi>d</mi><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub></mrow><mrow><mi>d</mi><mi>t</mi></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) R \ddot { R } + \frac { 3 } { 2 } \dot { R } ^ { 2 } ( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { 3 c } ) = ( 1 + \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) \frac { p _ { 1 } } { \rho } + \frac { R } { \rho c } \frac { d p _ { 1 } } { d t }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.16666em;">¨</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.26519em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.845108em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8141079999999999em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.519241em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4133239999999998em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.872331em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322159999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span> ,	(1.4)</p>
<p>where R denotes the bubble’s radius while ρ is the density of the liquid. Besides, the speed of sound in the liquid, C, is assumed to be a constant. The gas inside the bubble obeys the van der Waals law. Combined with the ambient pressure pstat, the pressure at the bubble wall p1 can be given as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mi>R</mi><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>¨</mo></mover><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><msup><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mrow><mn>3</mn><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mi>ρ</mi></mfrac><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mi>R</mi><mrow><mi>ρ</mi><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mfrac><mrow><mi>d</mi><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub></mrow><mrow><mi>d</mi><mi>t</mi></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) R \ddot { R } + \frac { 3 } { 2 } \dot { R } ^ { 2 } ( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { 3 c } ) = ( 1 + \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) \frac { p _ { 1 } } { \rho } + \frac { R } { \rho c } \frac { d p _ { 1 } } { d t }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.16666em;">¨</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.26519em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.845108em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8141079999999999em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.519241em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4133239999999998em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.872331em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322159999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span>(1.5)</p>
<p>where Rn is the equilibrium radius of the bubble, pv is the vapor pressure, μ is the dynamic viscosity, and σ is the surface tension coefficient of the liquid, and p(t) is the pressure of sound fields. Moreover, b is the van der Waals parameter given as 0.0016, while κ is the polytropic exponent denoted as 4/3. The concrete data used in calculations were retrieved from the references[46,48].</p>
<p>Herein, five groups of γ( 0.45=1.35mm/(2<em>1.5 mm), 0.80=2.40 mm /(2</em>1.5 mm), 1.0=3.0 mm /(2<em>1.5 mm), 1.47=2.94 mm /(2</em>1 mm), and 1.93=3.85 mm /(2*1 mm) ) were employed for experimental studies. The aforementioned cases represent that the ideal geometry of adjacent bubbles is mutually covered, squeezed, touched, about, and aloof. Lastly, more than 20 photos were taken every 5μs in the whole progress to assess the multi-bubbles dynamics for given conditions.</p>
<h1 id="iii-experimental-results">III. Experimental results</h1>
<p>In this section, experimental results of typical cases and their mechanisms are interpreted based on the shadowgraph and the simplified explanation of bubble-bubble interaction. In particular, this only considers the effect of an acoustic pressure wave of a bubble radiated on the other bubbles[49–51]. The dominant parameter in this work is γ, the non-dimension distance between two adjacent bubbles, which is defined in formula 1.1.</p>
<p>Figures 3, 5, 7, 9, 11 illustrates selected frames of the experimental photos of the dynamics of three symmetrical aligned in-phase bubbles for five typical distances. The main process of Figures 3-12 can be summarized as follows in terms of different values of γ and the relationship of the geometries of adjacent bubbles when they expand in isolation:</p>
<p>Case 1: Large γ (γ=1.93 in Figure 3), causes the isolated maximized geometries to leave each other. Two diameter-equaled space separated the bubbles at the maximum. They exhibited the weakest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 2: Large γ (γ=1.47 in Figure 5), causes the isolated maximized geometries to near to each other. Two radius-equaled space separated the bubbles at the maximum. They elucidated the second weakest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 3: Medium γ (γ=1.0 in Figure 7), causes the isolated maximized geometries to touch each other. The bubbles contacted to each other at the maximum radii and showed intermediate interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 4: Little γ (γ=0.80 in Figure 9), causes the isolated maximized geometries to squeeze each other. The bubbles contacted to each other before the maximum radii and had the second strongest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 5: Little γ (γ= 0.45 in Figure 11), causes the isolated maximized geometries to cover each other. The bubbles were quite close to each other, even have limited the early expanding significantly. In this case, bubbles had the strongest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="3"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr3.jpg" alt="fig3" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 3. Case 1: Large γ (γ=1.93) experimental results with the weakest interaction.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="4"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr4.jpg" alt="fig4" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 4. Parameters in Case 1.</p>
<p>In the figures above and below(Figure 3 - Figure13), t is the exact time and T0 is the first oscillation period of bubbles in isolation, while T = t/T0 is the normalized time. Usually, an isolated bubble expands before T = 0.5, reaching its maximum at T=0.5, then shrinks and eventually collapses at T = 1.</p>
<p>Figures 3 and 4 display the results of Case 1, γ = 1.93. Big initial separations induce weak bubble interactions. In Figure 3, the first frame reflects the starting of bubbles. The morphologies of bubbles nuclei are revealed to be similar to that of plasma calculated using a transient coupling model [47], which implies that this starting of bubbles follows the dynamics of the laser-induced plasma. Furthermore, based on the time series diagram, the deformation of the bubbles is primarily influenced by the initial shape. During the expansion period, the shadow area in frames 2, 3, 4 on the upper column, the volume of the center bubble was slightly smaller than that of the verge bubbles. This signifies that the phase of the center bubble is slightly delayed, and thus the verge bubbles reach the maximum bubble radius before the center one. Here, the phase was noted as the relative position of the bubbles' state of motion in a period， [34]. If the period of periodic motion is extended, the time when a bubble reaches a certain phase is delayed. Here, phase delayed means that the period of the first oscillation is extended. In shrinkage, the phase of the verge bubbles also precedes the center bubble. The interactions caused by the pressure and tension waves of bubbles radiation are gradually becoming apparent. As indicated in the first frame of the bottom column, the bubbles elongated, and the outer edge of the verge bubbles get flattened and then shrink faster than the inner edge. Subsequently, as shown in the second frame of the bottom column, the verge bubbles produce jets pointing toward the center bubble, which remains a larger volume. In the third frame of the bottom column, the verge bubbles collapse and produce shock waves, but the center bubble survives and continues shrinking. Finally, the center bubble collapse after the fourth frame. Whilst, the positions of rebound verge bubbles move towards the center.</p>
<p>Figure 4 depicts the normalized Rs and axes of bubbles and circularity over time. The distribution of Rs is flatter and wider compared to the K-M curve. This implies that the development of bubbles is inhibited. During the interactions of the bubbles, the energy of each bubble, which is converted to potential energy, is less than that of single bubbles so that the bubbles cannot reach its R0, and thus their phase is delayed. Here the phase delay was followed by a decrease of maximum radii due to the limited bubble energy. The center bubble was affected by two verge bubbles simultaneously, while the two verge bubbles were only affected by the center bubble because of the screen effect[40,41]. Therefore, the center bubble is more significantly inhibited, indicating a smaller Rmax and more phase delay than the verge bubbles. During the expansion, the A and B axes differed slightly. However, when the bubbles in both positions enter the shrinking phase, the negative radiation pressure will stretch the other bubbles, mainly on the B axis, and thereby elongating the B axis. Remarkably, the center bubble was stretched most, and hence its A and B axes were longer than that of the verge bubbles. The B-inner and B-outer based on the minimum bounding rectangle can not accurately describe the deformation of the verge bubbles due to the concave deformation. From the image of C, the C of verge bubbles become smaller at the end of the shrinkage, that is, at T= 1.05. On the other hand, the center bubble loses its C at T = 0.8 due to the stretching. Conclusively, the motion of bubbles in Case 1 is similar to that of an isolated single bubble, but the phase is slightly prolonged, the maximum radii are slightly smaller, and deformation occurs before the collapse.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr5.jpg" alt="fig5" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 5. Case 2: Large γ (γ =1.47), experimental results with the second weakest interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr6.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 6. Parameters in Case 2.</p>
<p>Figure 5 and 6 present the results of Case 2, γ = 1.47. Overall, the result was similar to that of Case 1. However, the smaller spacing between the bubbles enhanced their interaction, while some effects might be more pronounced for the multi-bubble system. The initial phase exhibited very little impact, like the second frame. The phase delay was more pronounced than Case 1. In addition, the inhibition of phase due to the interaction was similar to that of Case1. Comparing the four frames of third and fourth in the bottom columns of Figures 3 and 5, the collapse time of the two kinds of bubbles in Case 2 was delayed, with a higher time difference between the center and verge bubbles. The phase delay of the center bubble was apparent due to the dual inhibition of two verge bubbles. Thus, the T of stretching and collapse was delayed.</p>
<p>From the Rs graph, the curves of Case 2 are broader and lower than that of Case 1. The rebound of Case 2 is at T &gt; 1.1, while that of Case 1 is at T ≈ 1.1. Additionally, the maximum value of R in Case 2 was slightly lower than that of Case 1, and the reaching time is also delayed, which is the phase delay caused by inhibition. The difference between center and verge Rs also expands. From the axes graph, A, B, and R of verge bubbles are synchronized to reach the maximum and then contract, reach the minimum, and then rebound. On the other hand, A and B of the center bubble is synchronized with R during the expansion phase and is smaller than the A and B of verge bubbles. Thus, A-center is flatter and broader than axes of verge bubbles. The B-center separates from the other axis curves at T=0.65 and remains continuously high until it decreases after T = 1.0. This signifies the center bubble of Case 2 is elongated in the vertical direction.</p>
<p>Compared to Case 1, the bubble deformation in Case 2 was more pronounced. The C of verge bubbles rapidly decrease in the late stage of shrinkage, T = 1.0, due to the jets penetrating the bubbles. The rebound period also maintains a smaller C due to multi-bubble disturbance and unstable processes. The C of the elongated center bubble starts to decline slowly at T = 0.65, and eventually decreases sharply during the collapse phase. Finally, compared with Case 1, the overall deformation is more prominent, and the deformation time T is also advanced.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr7.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 7. Case 3: Medium γ (γ = 1.0) experimental results with intermediate interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr8.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 8. Parameters in Case 3.</p>
<p>Figures 7 and 8 show the results of Case 3, γ = 1.0. The interactions were more evident due to a closer spacing. As shown in the third frame of Figure 7, the expansion of the center bubble is inhibited. Consequently, the inner edges of the verge bubbles get flattened. Therefore, the centroids of verge bubbles form an offset due to the interaction of push. The fourth frame revealed that the verge bubbles reach near their maximum radii, while the phase of the center bubble lags far behind, and also its radius does not reach the maximum. Furthermore, both kinds of bubbles deform significantly, whereas the opposite surfaces get more flattened. As a result, the centroids of verge bubbles move towards the center bubble due to the shape change. As indicated in the fifth frame, when the center bubble reaches near the maximum radius, the verge bubbles begin to shrink. Between the fourth and fifth frames, there is no contact between the three bubbles, and there exist two thick gaps of water layers, the length of which are in the range of 0.3R0 - 0.4R0. Consequently, the verge bubbles shrink and form a stretch against the center bubble, as depicted in frame 6. Moreover, the verge bubbles form jets from the outer boundary towards the center bubble. The phase difference between bubbles gradually accumulates under the influence of the interaction. The center bubble continues to grow in the vertical direction, while the horizontal shrinkage is approximately synchronized with the verge bubbles, as viewed in frames 6, 7. Lastly, the jets penetrate the verge bubbles vertically. Then the verge bubbles collapse and rebound while the center bubble collapses and rebounds horizontally (as shown in frame 8). The collapse times are delayed compared to that of Case 2.</p>
<p>Figure 8 shows the normalized radii, axes, and circularity over time of Case 3. The initial expansion of bubbles follows the K-M model. When the pressure waves induced by expansion start to affect each other, the expansion is slowed down by a decrease in the differential pressure between inside and outside. As indicated in the radii graph, the R curves were clearly no longer symmetric curves of T = Tx (in K-M, Tx= 0.5). They become smoother with the growth of span. The maximum bubble radii that can be reached by the inner and outer bubbles are larger than that of K-M. The verge bubbles reached their maximum R at T = 0.5, while the center bubble reached its maximum R at T = 0.6. Both the center and verge bubbles maintained stable and maximum for a longer time duration significantly. This corresponds to the interaction of the tension waves generated by the shrinkage.</p>
<p>Overall, the axes of verge bubbles changed similarly to R. This is also consistent with the higher C, which means the bubbles have better circularity. The A and B of the center bubble were smaller than those of verge bubbles in the expanding stage. However, the center bubble begins to change apparently at T = 0.6 when it reached the maximum radius. The deceleration of A-center was slower, and its height was higher than the axes of verge bubbles because there are no adhesions, and also the effect of the tension wave is greater. The B-center continues to increase linearly to approximately T = 1.1 and then plummets due to the occurrence of collapse. This turn occurs faster and later than that of Case 2. The B-verge -outer is higher than the B-verge-inner, which indicates that the centroids of verge bubbles move towards the center, and their parts closer to the center bubble are wider. Finally, the deformation of the center bubble, which the A and B show, represent in C as a gradual smooth reduction starting at T = 0.6 and reaching a minimum at collapse.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr9.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 9. Case 4: Little γ (γ = 0.80) experimental results with the second strongest interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr10.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 10. Parameters in Case 4.</p>
<p>Figures 9and 10 show the results of Case4, γ = 0.8. From the second frame of the upper column, the initial evolution of the bubbles was still spherical. The phases of bubbles become different after the bubbles are affected by the pressure wave induced by other bubbles. In frame 3, the verge bubbles are significantly larger than the center bubble. This may be attributed to the effect of the inhibition described above. Thus the center and verge bubbles form a more evident phase difference. Whilst, the bubble expansions are inhibited, the contacted parts get flattened, and bubbles push each other. In frame 4, the verge bubbles begin to shrink. Under the combination of hydrostatic pressure, tensile force, and internal bubble pressure, the center bubble maintains maximum for a longer time than in K-M. Because of this mutual stretching, the space between the bubbles is reduced. In the frames of the bottom column, the center bubbles shrink but are also stretched by the verge bubbles to form a distinctive cylinder structure. Consequently, the opposite surfaces get flattened, while the vertical sides deform from the horizontal symmetry axis as well as the middle position of the vertical sides. In the second frame of the bottom column, distinct water films form between the bubbles. The verge bubbles collapse inward partly due to the jets. The horizontal shrinkage of the center bubbles was substantial. The opposite sides of the verge bubbles to the center bubble are stretched by the center bubble. The closer to the vertical symmetry axis and the center bubble, the slower the phase is. This phase delay creates inward jets on the outer boundaries. In frame 3 of the lower column, the jets from the verge bubble penetrates their bubbles and shoot into the center bubble, which continues to shrink, necking to a remarkable hourglass. In the later stage, the center bubble may collapse at the waist of the hourglass. In frame 4 below, the verge bubble collapses completely, and their residual gas is mixed with the residual gas from the center bubble. The phase of the center part of the center bubble is more advanced, resulting in rebound earlier than the other part. However, due to the unstable of residual gas and water, the center bubble collapses to a complex state. The time of jets forming and collapse was delayed compared to that of Case 3. In cases where γ is small enough, bubbles may develop an outspread adhesion in the opposite centers during oscillation. Although significant boundary gaps can still be observed, as disclosed in frame 7. Under this circumstance, when we processed the images, we connected the closest two points of two gaps, and deemed the lines as the boundaries of bubbles, without considering the influence of jets on R in the three-dimensional scale. Then we calculate the parameters of bubbles as mentioned in the experimental setup.</p>
<p>Figure 10 outlines the normalized radii, axes, and circularity over time of Case 4. The R curves were smoother with the loss of symmetry. After reaching their maximum value, Rs changed slowly and remain at a relatively high level. The initial stage of expansion was slightly different than that of K-M. As the pressure waves from the other bubbles reached the exact bubble, its expansion was gradually inhibited. The center bubble was affected by double interactions, and thus its inhibition was bigger, which leads to its more phase delay. Additionally, the R of the center bubble was smaller than that of verge bubbles in the expansion, but bigger in shrinkage. The verge bubbles reached their maximum radii within a short time after T = 0.5 and then declined slowly. On the other hand, the center bubble reached its maximum radius near T = 0.8, and then decline slower than the verge bubbles. Here, the difference between Rs and K-M was bigger than in Case 3.</p>
<p>The B of the center bubble in the axes graph of Figure 8 reveals a sharp contraction at the end of shrinkage. However, in Figure 10, it has only two stages namely growth and stabilization. The stable stage extends to the right of the figure until the cavitation bubble is broken. Thus we can treat it as the turn we mentioned in Case 2 and 3, of this curve moved towards a positive direction. This is because after the bubble is pulled into a cylinder, its shrinkage is mainly reflected as an hourglass shrinkage, and in deformation. After fracturing at the waist, the minimum bounding rectangle of the remnant center bubble changed slightly. The B-inner of the verge bubbles was more affected, and therefore smaller than the B-outer. In comparison, the difference between B-verge-inner and B-verge-outer become bigger than that of Case 3. This suggests that the centroid translation caused by the deformation gets more evident. The As of the center and verge bubbles change synchronously because the tension at the opposite and contact surfaces is balanced. The contraction did not occur at the width of the minimum bounding rectangle, and thus As may exhibit high value and decline slowly. The C of Case 4 starts to decline slowly at T = 0.2, while in Case 3 it is at T = 0.6. This was caused by the squeeze. Cs remain high during the expansion period. The C-center was smaller because the center bubbles are squeezed greater. When shrink, the shape of the verge bubbles is flattened by the jets, and the center bubble necks to an hourglass. Their Cs gradually get smaller and decrease violently as the shrinkage progresses. Meanwhile, the verge bubbles deform violently, resulting in a smaller C-verge.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr11.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 11. Case 5: Little γ (γ = 0.45) experimental results with the strongest interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr12.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 12. Parameters in Case 5.</p>
<p>Figures 11 and 12 show Case 5, γ = 0.45. The second and third frames on the top column are the early stage of bubble expansion. Bubbles got flat at the opposite position to each other while the other positions expand as normal. The opposite surfaces got nearly parallel. The closer to the vertical symmetric axis, the earlier the surface becomes flat. The length of parallel surfaces increases over time before reaching the maximum. In the fourth frame on the top column, the center bubble grows to a cylinder because of the squeezing of two verge bubbles; the verge bubbles grew like straight mouth bowls with a round bottom at the same time. Water films persisted between the bubbles.</p>
<p>The contact surfaces continue expanding due to the increased pressure difference caused by the bubble interaction. The verge bubbles evolved into an open bowl, while the side of the center bubble looks like a hyperbola. The central part of the center bubble started to shrink as the internal pressure was released. The squeezing caused the parts to move out of phase, and the bubbles were unable to reach their maximum radii at the same time. In the vertical parts of the bubbles, the phase was more advanced, whereas, in the second frame in the lower column, the upper and lower bubbles form jets in the vertical symmetrical axis. Additionally, we can still observe the delineation of bubbles. Since the phase at the contact parts was delayed, the bubbles as a whole exhibited a cross shape shrinkage. The phase of the non-contact parts of the center bubble was later than that of the verge bubbles due to the double action of the other two bubbles. The cross shrinkage is mainly reflected in the vertical direction. The last frame indicated that the bubbles finally collapse vertically and radiate shockwaves outwards, ending up a dish-shaped remnant. The center bubble was smaller than the verge bubbles in the expansion but bigger in the shrinkage. Overall, the lifetimes of the three bubbles were nearly equal, and being longer than those in Case 4.</p>
<p>Figure 12 shows the normalized radii, axes, and circularity over the normalized time of Case 5. The Rs still obeyed the K-M model of isolated single bubble expansion in the early stage of cavitation. When the pressure fields of bubbles induced begin to influence each other, the pressure waves increase the external pressure and hence reduced the pressure difference. Thus, the progress of R was inhibited. The asymmetry of R curves gets more evident. When expanded, the center bubble was subjected to the pressure wave of both verge bubbles. Its external pressure is higher than the others, the pressure difference is less, and the inhibition is larger, while the verge bubbles are only affected by the pressure of the center bubble due to the isolation effect of the center bubble, and also receive less inhibition. Therefore, the verge bubbles reach the maximum radii before the center bubble, but later than that of an isolated single bubble in the first oscillation period. The difference between maximum Rs of the center bubble and that of the verge bubbles reached was small. Besides, they are all smaller than those in the K-M model and Case 4. Meanwhile, Rs changes more slightly than in Case 4. In the early shrink stage, the internal pressure was lower than the external pressure. Bubbles radiate a pulling force pointing to itself. Therefore, the difference between the internal and external pressure of other bubbles become less, and the oscillation gets inhibition. Bubbles shrink synchronously in the vertical; thus, the difference between Rs of the center and verge bubbles are small. Generally, for the center bubble, the period was more extensive; the phase was delayed due to it receiving larger inhibition.</p>
<p>On the axes graph, we can observe the inhibitory effect more clearly. At the primary stage of the bubble, it expands rapidly. After the normalized length reaches about 0.3, the expansion slowed down significantly. Then Bs stabilizes near the maximum and slowly declines after reaching the maximum. The B-inners were more severely affected, which represents the length of the opposite surface to the centroids. When B-verge-inner +B-center = 0.9 = 2*γ, the edges of the isolated expanding bubbles should contact each other. However, we observed in the column above, that there was a presence of water film. The continuous growth of the short axis was accompanied by the displacement of the relative position of bubbles. The interaction between the bubbles forms a push that pushes the verge bubbles away from the center bubbles. As mentioned above, the center bubble is affected by two pressure fields, while the verge bubbles were affected by only one pressure field. Thus, B of the center bubble is smaller than that of the verge bubbles. In addition, the difference between B-verge-outer and B-verge-inner was more apparent than that of Case 4. This purports that the shift of verge bubble centroids is considerable while the mutual extension of the inter-bubble joints is stable.</p>
<p>Particularly, when T = 0.4, the Bs reach the maximum, as well the bubble distances, as denoted in Figure 11, upper frame 4. After this point, the bubble energy is released mainly through the mutual extension of the inter-bubble joints. Subsequently, As refers to the length of the joint, which appears a process of re-growth. In this re-growth progress, the As of center and verge bubbles change synchronously and reach their maximum at approximately T=0.8. However, there exists a small difference because the center bubble shrinks horizontally while the verge bubbles predominately shrink along the vertical direction. Hence, the axes cannot accurately describe the bowl-shaped deformation of verge bubbles and the hyperbolic deformation of the center bubble. Therefore, C becomes an excellent auxiliary parameter to describe the deformation. From the circularity graph in the upper column of Figure 12, it can be viewed that the beginning of the circularity loss is earlier than T=0.1. The deformation of the center bubble is more than that of verge bubbles. Then at T = 0.4, the C-center dropped a sudden. This progress corresponds to the mutual extension of the inter-bubble joints after the bubbles contact each other. The C flatten out when the R reaches the maximum, and rise due to the global shrinkage of the center bubble. Afterward, it declined after T = 1.0 because the vertical shrinkage of the center plays a significant role.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr13.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 13. The normalized distance of different case. Little γ receives a greater push effect.</p>
<p>Figure 13 shows the results of normalized bubble distance,   over time in case 5.   can be used as a measure of the bubble interactions, while   = 1 represents the initial position of the bubble center. A bigger   indicates that the bubbles are far away from each other, whereas a smaller   means they are close to each other. Furthermore,   reflects the effect of bubbles radiated pressure waves on other bubbles. Also, it shows the movement of verge bubbles, while on the other hand, it reflects their deformation. If the proximal and distal ends are fixed, the deformation also changes the centroids. The flattening of the opposite surface of bubbles makes   smaller. Likewise, jets produced and penetrated inwards would also make   smaller. Here, the effects of these two factors are considered indiscriminately as the centroid distance change is caused by bubbles interaction.</p>
<p>Due to the geometrical attenuation of the radiated pressure waves, the closer the position is in the same direction of the assumed spherical bubble, the stronger is the sound pressure. The smaller the γ is, the larger the ratio of stress surface to radiation wave sphere is, and the more evident is the forced effect. Therefore, the smaller the γ is, the more apparent is the effect of the inter -bubble force. As shown in the graph, the smaller the γ is, then, the larger the maximum value of   is, the faster the  changes, and the later   reaches its maximum. This indicates that the closer the bubbles are to each other, the more energy is used to push the adjacent bubbles away. After   exceeds 1, the time of falling below 1 decreases with γ increasing. This means the bigger the γ is, the sooner it can stop pushing each other around and return to its original position. In the shrinking phase before T = 1.0, that is, none bubbles have rebounded, the smaller the γ is, the steeper the curve becomes. Thus it indicates that the larger the γ is, the greater the potential energy accumulated, the longer the acceleration distance is, and the faster the movement is. These also tell that the time duration of the negative pressure radiated by bubbles is broad enough to complete the process.</p>
<p>When γ = 1.93, the push between the bubbles is almost negligible. However, in the shrinking phase,   decreases, in part due to the proximity of bubbles, as well as the deformation caused by jets. In the rebound phase, the verge bubbles penetrated by jets rebound with movement inward, thus the   decreases.</p>
<p>In Case 2, γ = 1.47, it can be noted that the part above  =1 has a certain curvature. The push effect was greater than Case 1. Meanwhile, at the pull stage, the curve turns earlier.<br>
When γ = 1.0, the push and pull between bubbles were notable. The difference in the time phase between bubbles increases, while the center bubble collapses laterally in a stick shape with stable length. Moreover, the verge bubbles re-expanded in the direction of the jets,   decreases significantly.</p>
<p>In the case of γ = 0.8, 0.45, the push and pull between bubbles were more apparent. At the shrinking phase of Case 4, the center bubble collapsed in an hourglass shape. Also, it may disintegrate at the vertical center. Thereafter, the two separated parts will move outward and merge with verge bubbles, and then collapse near the position of verge bubbles. Therefore, in this case, the   is small but larger compared to that in case 3. On the other hand, in Case 5, center and verge bubbles collapsed in a disk-shape. The denominator of  ，D0， is little enough so that the change in the trend of   is not too obvious. Besides, the phase difference between center and verge bubbles was quite little at collapse, so that simultaneous collapse and rebounding does not occur.</p>
<h1 id="iv-discussion">IV. Discussion</h1>
<p>Bubbles can be treated as symmetrically aligned in-phase bubbles, taking into account the isolation effect and ignoring the small angular shifts in the arrangement between the bubbles. The behavior of bubbles at different positions can be approximated to different existing examples. For instance, the center bubble is restricted in two directions, and its oscillation is similar to that of a bubble between two parallel rigid boundaries. The verge bubbles, on the other hand, are inhibited in one direction and thus exhibit similar patterns as if they were bubbles near a rigid boundary. Jets are formed towards the center bubble during the shrinking phase. However, in the experiments, since the three laser beams are focused from the same lens, there is an inevitable focus shift at a larger incident angle at the time of breakdown. Thus the three points are not strictly linearly aligned but form a specific small angular offset. At this point, the interactions between the bubbles are different from the aforementioned analogy. The center bubble receives the action of bubbles on both sides, not in a straight line, but an angle. The behavior of center bubbles can be analogized to bubbles in different angular structures. In the experimental figures, the left and right boundaries of the center bubbles during the shrinking phase are not symmetrical. Notably, in Figures 9 and 11, the shape of the formed jets are asymmetric. These are all problems caused by the directionality of multiple pressures. The situation can be approximated as described elsewhere[38,52–57] partly. Here, we ignore the little angular shift due to the screen effect and symmetry. The interaction between the bubbles can be simplified as the interaction between bubbles and their acoustic radiation When the bubble is a spherical one, the time-varying sound pressure of its far-field can be expressed as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>p</mi><mi>a</mi></msub><mo>(</mo><mi>r</mi><mo separator="true">,</mo><mi>t</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>ρ</mi><mi>L</mi></msub><mrow><mn>4</mn><mi>π</mi><mi>r</mi></mrow></mfrac><mfrac><mrow><msup><mi>d</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi>V</mi></mrow><mrow><mi>d</mi><msup><mi>t</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">p _ { a } ( r , t ) = \frac { \rho _ { L } } { 4 \pi r } \frac { d ^ { 2 } V } { d t ^ { 2 } }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.151392em;"><span style="top:-2.5500000000000003em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.15em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mpunct">,</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault">t</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.36292em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">4</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">π</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.3448em;"><span style="top:-2.3567071428571427em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">L</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.14329285714285717em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.01792em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7463142857142857em;"><span style="top:-2.786em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8913142857142857em;"><span style="top:-2.931em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.22222em;">V</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span>(1.6)</p>
<p>where pa refers to the sound pressure of the far-field radiation, r refers to the distance from the center of the bubble to the measuring point, ρL refers to the liquid density, and V(t) represents the time-varying volume of the bubble[49]. After determining the measuring position and the relative direction of the bubble, it is reasonable to extend this formula to the radiation acoustic pressure of non-spherical bubbles based on the change of the bubble radius in one direction[58], which is</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>p</mi><mi>a</mi></msub><mo>(</mo><mi>R</mi><mo separator="true">,</mo><mi>r</mi><mo separator="true">,</mo><mi>t</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>ρ</mi><mi>L</mi></msub><mi>r</mi></mfrac><mo>⋅</mo><mi>R</mi><mo>⋅</mo><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><msup><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>+</mo><mi>R</mi><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>¨</mo></mover><mo>)</mo></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">p _ { a } ( R , r , t ) = \frac { \rho _ { L } } { r } \cdot R \cdot ( 2 \dot { R } ^ { 2 } + R \ddot { R } )</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.151392em;"><span style="top:-2.5500000000000003em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.15em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mpunct">,</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mpunct">,</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault">t</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.0925em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.3448em;"><span style="top:-2.3567071428571427em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">L</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.14329285714285717em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">⋅</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.68333em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">⋅</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.17019em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">2</span><span class="mord"><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8141079999999999em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.17019em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.16666em;">¨</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span></span>(1.7)</p>
<p>where R(t) refers to the change of bubble radius along the direction of r. By substituting this sound pressure to the external acoustic pressure term p(t) in the K-M model, the pulsation of the bubbles affected by the far-field sound pressure can be obtained. The dimensional situation studied in this paper cannot be completely expressed by the far-field pressure. When being affected, the bubbles will lose their sphere, while their boundary and the pressure of the outward radiation will change. However, it is still quite reasonable to explain the effects suffered by bubbles using sound pressure [41]. In this regard, we can simply divide the affected bubble radiation pressure into three processes. See attached Figure 23 from the literature [51]: stage a. high-pressure pulses and constantly decreased positive pressures in the initial expansion phase; stage b. negative pressure in the stable phase; and stage c. positive pressure and high-pressure pulses formed at the end of the shrinkage. As mentioned earlier, the stage a may slow down the expansion of bubbles. Moreover, the center bubble is affected by multiple stage as and becomes slower. The stage b increases the expansion, blocks the shrinkage and causes the stretching of the bubbles, which maintain a large radius in the direction of the force for more time. The stage c accelerates the collapse or decelerate the rebound of adjacent bubbles. Since the affected collapse is directional, the results of the mentioned cases are also different. For example, in Case 1 - 2, the pressure of the verge bubble on the center bubble almost cancels out the deformation caused by stage b, while the center bubble does inhibit the rebound of the verge bubbles. In Case3 - 4, the shrinkage of the center bubble is primarily reflected in the horizontal direction. Thus, the pressure wave of center bubble formed in stage b and stage c is mainly transmitted in the horizontal direction. It is difficult to influence the verge bubbles. The effect of the verge bubbles on the center bubble is reflected in the flattening of the opposite surfaces and accelerated contraction. In Case 5, due to its proximity and phase synchronization, the three bubbles can be considered as a whole, and thus the effects of stage c can be ignored.</p>
<p>The pressure waves associated with the above three stages modify the distribution of internal and external pressure of adjacent bubbles, instead of uniform pressure difference as isolated spherical bubbles. The internal and external pressure distribution of the bubbles is determined by direction, which makes the oscillation of the bubbles in different directions show a large difference. Thus, we can assume that the radius change in different directions within a bubble has different periods, that is, a bubble has different time phases in different directions. In a bubble, the phase is delayed, where it is affected by pressure waves. For instance, where the external pressure is higher, the phase is highly delayed. The direction with the later phase reaches the maximum radius later as well as the minimum radius, namely collapse. As a result, deformation will occur. The part with the advance phase reaches the maximum, while the other one with the later phase does not reach the maximum. Then the advance phase part begins to shrink, whereas the part with the later phase has just reached its maximum. This process is often accompanied by the transposition of the bubble long axis. When the advance phase part starts to shrink sharply, the delayed phase part just starts to shrink. Therefore, forming specific deformation, for example, jets from the advance phase part to the delayed part.</p>
<p>In this work, the center bubble experienced more pressure than the verge bubbles. In addition, the ensemble phase of the center bubble was delayed more compared to that of verge bubbles. Hence, the lifetime of a center bubble is longer, the radius smaller than verge bubbles. When one specifically analyzes the individual bubble, the center bubble is first affected by the pressure wave along the vertical direction. Thus the phase delay decreases as the distance from the opposite surface to a certain position vertically increases. The central part is affected later; the phase is in advance. Therefore, as described earlier, the axis transposition, special cylindrical shape, and special forms of collapse will form. Moreover, the opposite position of the verge bubbles to the center bubble is first affected by the pressure wave, and thus its phase is later. On the other hand, the backside position in the verge bubbles is later affected by the pressure wave, and thus the phase is in advance. As a result, the oscillation of the leeward boundary in the verge bubbles precedes the windward boundary. The leeward boundary shrinks violently while the windward boundary is in the stable stage. Then the inward jet is formed on the leeward boundary. The verge bubbles in different cases form jets at different times, due to their different time phase difference between their anterior and posterior surfaces.</p>
<p>This method of dividing the interior of bubbles into different phases can be extended to the bubble arrays. Each bubble in the array can be treated as a part of the bubble described above. As noted in the literature [59], since the corner bubbles are further away from the geometric center, it can be treated as the expanded parts with advanced phase in a single bubble by analogy. Hence collapse starts from an angle rather than the edge. This perhaps may be another way to understand the direction of the collapse except for curvature.</p>
<p>Geometrically, for the R, we define based on shadow, and for a volume given bubble, the spherical bubble has the smallest max(R). Furthermore, the max(R) might become larger when bubbles lose their sphericity in deformation. In the interaction of the multiple bubbles, if the volume of the bubble does not change, the max(R) should be larger. However, each of the max(R) we measured was becoming smaller, which suggests that the volume of the bubbles affected by the interaction did not reach the maximum volume that the isolated bubbles can reach.</p>
<p>The process of bubble expansion can be regarded as a process of kinetic energy transformed into potential energy. When the internal pressure of a bubble is greater than the external pressure, it is therefore the difference between the internal and external pressure that drives work to achieve the transformation. After exceeding the equilibrium radius, the internal pressure of the bubble is less than the external pressure. The bubble transforms the residual kinetic energy into potential energy through inertia. When multiple bubbles interact, the bubble energy is not only transformed from kinetic energy to potential energy but also a part of the kinetic energy transfer that makes the bubble position move relatively. During expansion, there is a push effect in bubbles that keeps adjacent bubbles away from themselves. When bubbles are far away, the multi-bubble system accumulates potential energy. During shrinkage, the potential energy of the bubble system is transformed into kinetic energy, including the kinetic energy of bubble shrinkage as well as the bubble movement. This process is a unified process relevant to the equilibrium radius. However, since the driving force of the two transformations in this process is not the same one, they have some independence. Thus, the time of the maximum bubble radius and the maximum distance do not coincide.</p>
<p>Without the consideration of the change of deformation to R, max(R) is directly used to calculate the bubble energy E= (4/3)π(max(R))3p0. The normalized bubble energy  is obtained by comparing it to E0, using R0 in the energy equation.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>γ=0.45</th>
<th>γ=0.80</th>
<th>γ=1.0</th>
<th>γ=1.47</th>
<th>γ=1.93</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Center bubble</td>
<td>0.7360</td>
<td>0.7584</td>
<td>0.7895</td>
<td>0.7833</td>
<td>0.8507</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Verge bubbles</td>
<td>0.7115</td>
<td>0.7216</td>
<td>0.7502</td>
<td>0.7994</td>
<td>0.8702</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sum</td>
<td>2.1590</td>
<td>2.2015</td>
<td>2.2898</td>
<td>2.3820</td>
<td>2.5911</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Tablet 1. Normalized bubble energy</p>
<p>In the table above, the maximum 20 values for each set of R are averaged and then calculate  . The Sum column is the result of one center bubble plus two verge bubbles. It can be noted that as γ decreases, the bubble energy contained in bubbles with maximum radius is declining. This implies that the bubble energy transformed into the bubble potential energy is increasing, which is consistent with our results of the pushing distance  .</p>
<h1 id="v-conclusion">V. Conclusion</h1>
<p>In this work, the dynamics of three uniformly separated laser-induced bubbles were experimentally studied. The precise control of distance and energy achieves the multi-bubbles interaction in one life period under ideal conditions. As a parameter of evenly distributed multi-cavitation space, γ is the main parameter in this study. The study shows:</p>
<ol>
<li>In bubble arrays, the lifetime of each bubble is generally extended, while the volume is reduced. This phenomenon is most apparent for the center bubble because of the most inhibition it received. In shrinkage, the lifetime difference causes the collapse of bubbles to proceed in an orderly manner, from the outside to the inside. Meanwhile, the smaller the γ, the more evident is this phenomenon.</li>
<li>The different phase delay in different parts of a bubble causes the unique shape of bubbles. From a relatively independent perspective, it can be considered that for the inner part of a bubble, the closer it is to the adjacent bubble, the more the phase delay. This phenomenon is achieved through the interaction between the bubbles and the acoustic radiation of the cavitation pulsation. The acoustic radiation changes the pressure difference between the interior and exterior of bubbles, which has an inhibitory effect on the continuous motion at the corresponding pulsation phase, thus delaying the phase of bubble parts.</li>
<li>In the three-bubble system with the same initial phase and equal spacing, there are various forms of the collapse of the center bubble: normal collapse; slightly elongated in the direction of alignment; elongating to a long stick; necking to an hourglass. When the γ is sufficiently small, the compression effect is more efficacious than stretching, then the center bubble was compacted to a dish. The center bubbles do not produce jets, while the verge bubbles produce jets towards the center, and the jets become stronger as the γ decreases. The beginning of the loss of circularity, which generally indicates the stability of the shape of bubbles, can occur at any stage. It moves forward as the γ decreases, from the end of shrinkage to the beginning of bubbles.</li>
<li>During the oscillation of the bubble array, the bubbles interact with each other through acoustic radiation, and the energy transfer changes the relative position of the bubbles. In expansion, the verge bubbles are pushed outward, while in shrinkage, they are pulled inward. The smaller the γ, the more apparent is the phenomenon.<br>
The interaction of multiple cavitation bubbles is discussed in this paper. The parameters R, A, B, C, and D are used to describe the interaction. However, further parameters describing the deformation during the interaction are needed especially in future research. Also, the lifetime extensions require to be quantified. The fate of the cavitation energy needs more accurate measurements. Whilst, the experimental method should be improved to obtain more accurate information about the bubbles in interaction. Therefore, further improvement should focus on the multiple bubbles dynamics in more detailed cases of parameter γ &lt; 1. Of note, this research provides valuable information for further understanding of the mechanism of multiple cavitation bubbles in medical and hydraulic engineering.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</h1>
<p>This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No.11774176).</p>
<h1 id="references">References</h1>
<p>[1]	N. Ochiai, J. Ishimoto, Numerical analysis of the effect of bubble distribution on multiple-bubble behavior, Ultrason. Sonochem. 61 (2020) 104818. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2019.104818.<br>
[2]	R. Timm, Optical and acoustic investigations of the dynamics of laser-produced cavitation bubbles near a solid boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 206 (1989) 299–338. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112089002314.<br>
[3]	S. LI, Cavitation enhancement of silt erosion—An envisaged micro model, Wear. 260 (2006) 1145–1150. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.WEAR.2005.07.002.<br>
[4]	W. Lauterborn, H. Bolle, Experimental investigations of cavitation-bubble collapse in the neighbourhood of a solid boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 72 (1975) 391–399. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112075003448.<br>
[5]	P. Cui, A.-M.M. Zhang, S. Wang, B.C. Khoo, Ice breaking by a collapsing bubble, J. Fluid Mech. 841 (2018) 287–309. https://doi.org/10.1017/jfm.2018.63.<br>
[6]	N. Vyas, Q.X. Wang, K.A. Manmi, R.L. Sammons, S.A. Kuehne, A.D. Walmsley, How does ultrasonic cavitation remove dental bacterial biofilm?, Ultrason. Sonochem. 67 (2020) 105112. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105112.<br>
[7]	C. Ohl, T. Kurz, R. Geisler, O. Lindau, W. Lauterborn, Bubble dynamics, shock waves and sonoluminescence, Philos. Trans. R. Soc. London. Ser. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci. 357 (1999) 269–294. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsta.1999.0327.<br>
[8]	P.M. Kanthale, P.R. Gogate, A.B. Pandit, A. Marie Wilhelm, Cavity cluster approach for quantification of cavitational intensity in sonochemical reactors, Ultrason. Sonochem. 10 (2003) 181–189. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1350-4177(03)00088-9.<br>
[9]	F. Reuter, S. Lesnik, K. Ayaz-Bustami, G. Brenner, R. Mettin, Bubble size measurements in different acoustic cavitation structures: Filaments, clusters, and the acoustically cavitated jet, Ultrason. Sonochem. 55 (2019) 383–394. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2018.05.003.<br>
[10]	D.H. Peregrine, The Acoustic Bubble. By T. G. Leighton. Academic Press, 1994. 613 pp. 95. ISBN 0-12-441920-8., J. Fluid Mech. 272 (1994) 407–408. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112094214519.<br>
[11]	Lord Rayleigh, VIII. On the pressure developed in a liquid during the collapse of a spherical cavity, London, Edinburgh, Dublin Philos. Mag. J. Sci. 34 (1917) 94–98. https://doi.org/10.1080/14786440808635681.<br>
[12]	W. Lauterborn, C.D. Ohl, Cavitation bubble dynamics, Ultrason. Sonochem. (1997). https://doi.org/10.1016/S1350-4177(97)00009-6.<br>
[13]	M. Reiner, On volume-or isotropic flow as exemplified in the creep of concrete, Flow, Turbul. Combust. 1 (1949) 475.<br>
[14]	E.A. Brujan, K. Nahen, P. Schmidt, A. Vogel, Dynamics of laser-induced cavitation bubbles near an elastic boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 433 (2001) 251–281. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112000003347.<br>
[15]	D. Obreschkow, P. Kobel, N. Dorsaz, A. De Bosset, C. Nicollier, M. Farhat, Cavitation bubble dynamics inside liquid drops in microgravity, Phys. Rev. Lett. (2006). https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.97.094502.<br>
[16]	S. Poulain, G. Guenoun, S. Gart, W. Crowe, S. Jung, Particle Motion Induced by Bubble Cavitation, Phys. Rev. Lett. 114 (2015) 214501. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.114.214501.<br>
[17]	J.B. Keller, M. Miksis, Bubble oscillations of large amplitude, J. Acoust. Soc. Am. 68 (1980) 628–633. https://doi.org/10.1121/1.384720.<br>
[18]	W. Lauterborn, T. Kurz, Physics of bubble oscillations, Reports Prog. Phys. 73 (2010) 106501. https://doi.org/10.1088/0034-4885/73/10/106501.<br>
[19]	J.R. Blake, G.S. Keen, R.P. Tong, M. Wilson, Acoustic cavitation: The fluid dynamics of non-spherical bubbles, Philos. Trans. R. Soc. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci. 357 (1999) 251–267. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsta.1999.0326.<br>
[20]	A. Biesheuvel, L. V. Wijngaarden, Two-phase flow equations for a dilute dispersion of gas bubbles in liquid, J. Fluid Mech. 148 (1984) 301–318. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112084002366.<br>
[21]	D.Z. Zhang, A. Prosperetti, Ensemble phase-averaged equations for bubbly flows, Phys. Fluids. 6 (1994) 2956–2970. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.868122.<br>
[22]	D. Fuster, T. Colonius, Modelling bubble clusters in compressible liquids, J. Fluid Mech. 688 (2011) 352–389. https://doi.org/10.1017/jfm.2011.380.<br>
[23]	M. Arora, C.D. Ohl, D. Lohse, Effect of nuclei concentration on cavitation cluster dynamics, J. Acoust. Soc. Am. 121 (2007) 3432. https://doi.org/10.1121/1.2722045.<br>
[24]	G. Servant, J.L. Laborde, A. Hita, J.P. Caltagirone, A. Gérard, On the interaction between ultrasound waves and bubble clouds in mono- and dual-frequency sonoreactors, Ultrason. Sonochem. 10 (2003) 347–355. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1350-4177(03)00105-6.<br>
[25]	E. Johnsen, T. Colonius, Shock-induced collapse of a gas bubble in shockwave lithotripsy, J. Acoust. Soc. Am. 124 (2008) 2011–2020. https://doi.org/10.1121/1.2973229.<br>
[26]	M.R. Betney, B. Tully, N.A. Hawker, Y. Ventikos, Computational modelling of the interaction of shock waves with multiple gas-filled bubbles in a liquid, Phys. Fluids. 27 (2015) 1–28. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.4914133.<br>
[27]	W. Lauterborn, T. Kurz, R. Geisler, D. Schanz, O. Lindau, Acoustic cavitation, bubble dynamics and sonoluminescence, Ultrason. Sonochem. 14 (2007) 484–491. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2006.09.017.<br>
[28]	A. Shima, The Natural Frequencies of Two Spherical Bubbles Oscillating in Water, J. Basic Eng. 93 (1971) 426–431. https://doi.org/10.1115/1.3425268.<br>
[29]	H.N. Oguz, A. Prosperetti, A generalization of the impulse and virial theorems with an application to bubble oscillations, J. Fluid Mech. 218 (1990) 143. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112090000957.<br>
[30]	R. Mettin, I. Akhatov, U. Parlitz, C.D. Ohl, W. Lauterborn, Bjerknes forces between small cavitation bubbles in a strong acoustic field, Phys. Rev. E. 56 (1997) 2924–2931. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.56.2924.<br>
[31]	A. HARKIN, T.J. KAPER, A.L.I. NADIM, Coupled pulsation and translation of two gas bubbles in a liquid, J. Fluid Mech. 445 (2001) 377–411. https://doi.org/10.1017/s0022112001005857.<br>
[32]	A. Shima, T. Fujiwara, The behavior of two bubbles near a solid wall, Arch. Appl. Mech. 62 (1992) 53–61. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00786681.<br>
[33]	B. Han, K. Köhler, K. Jungnickel, R. Mettin, W. Lauterborn, A. Vogel, Dynamics of laser-induced bubble pairs, J. Fluid Mech. 771 (2015) 706–742. https://doi.org/10.1017/jfm.2015.183.<br>
[34]	S.W. Fong, D. Adhikari, E. Klaseboer, B.C. Khoo, Interactions of multiple spark-generated bubbles with phase differences, Exp. Fluids. 46 (2009) 705–724. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00348-008-0603-4.<br>
[35]	P.A. Quinto-Su, C.D. Ohl, Interaction between two laser-induced cavitation bubbles in a quasi-two-dimensional geometry, J. Fluid Mech. 633 (2009) 425–435. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112009008064.<br>
[36]	P. Cui, Q.X. Wang, S.P. Wang, A.M. Zhang, Experimental study on interaction and coalescence of synchronized multiple bubbles, Phys. Fluids. 28 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1063/1.4939007.<br>
[37]	W. Lauterborn, T. Kurz, R. Mettin, C.D. Ohl, Experimental and Theoretical Bubble Dynamics, 2007. https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470141694.ch5.<br>
[38]	H. Chen, Z. Chen, Y. Li, Modulation of the secondary Bjerknes force in multi-bubble systems, Ultrason. Sonochem. 61 (2020) 104814. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2019.104814.<br>
[39]	J.P. Dear, J.E. Field, A.J. Walton, Gas compression and jet formation in cavities collapsed by a shock wave, Nature. 332 (1988) 505–508. https://doi.org/10.1038/332505a0.<br>
[40]	J.P. Dear, J.E. Field, A study of the collapse of arrays of cavities, J. Fluid Mech. 190 (1988) 409–425. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112088001387.<br>
[41]	N. Bremond, M. Arora, S.M. Dammer, D. Lohse, Interaction of cavitation bubbles on a wall, Phys. Fluids. 18 (2006) 121505. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.2396922.<br>
[42]	N. Bremond, M. Arora, C.D. Ohl, D. Lohse, Controlled multibubble surface cavitation, Phys. Rev. Lett. 96 (2006) 1–4. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.224501.<br>
[43]	E. Lauer, X.Y. Hu, S. Hickel, N.A. Adams, Numerical investigation of collapsing cavity arrays, Phys. Fluids. 24 (2012). https://doi.org/10.1063/1.4719142.<br>
[44]	L.W. Chew, E. Klaseboer, S.W. Ohl, B.C. Khoo, Interaction of two differently sized oscillating bubbles in a free field, Phys. Rev. E - Stat. Nonlinear, Soft Matter Phys. 84 (2011) 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.84.066307.<br>
[45]	S. Hysing, S. Turek, D. Kuzmin, N. Parolini, E. Burman, S. Ganesan, L. Tobiska, Quantitative benchmark computations of two-dimensional bubble dynamics, Int. J. Numer. Methods Fluids. 60 (2009) 1259–1288. https://doi.org/10.1002/fld.1934.<br>
[46]	D. Kröninger, K. Köhler, T. Kurz, W. Lauterborn, Particle tracking velocimetry of the flow field around a collapsing cavitation bubble, Exp. Fluids. 48 (2010) 395–408. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00348-009-0743-1.<br>
[47]	C. Zhang, J. Lu, H. Zhang, Z. Shen, X. Ni, Transient Coupling Model of Plasma and Laser Field in Water, IEEE J. Quantum Electron. 52 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1109/JQE.2016.2588465.<br>
[48]	W. Lauterborn, A. Vogel, Shock wave emission by laser generated bubbles, 2013. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-34297-4_3.<br>
[49]	C.E. Brennen, Cavitation and bubble dynamics, Cambridge University Press, 2013. https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107338760.<br>
[50]	C.D. Ohl, S.W. Ohl, ShockWave interaction with single bubbles and bubble clouds, in: Bubble Dyn. Shock Waves, Springer Berlin Heidelberg, 2013: pp. 3–31. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-34297-4_1.<br>
[51]	L. Lv, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Experimental investigations of the particle motions induced by a laser-generated cavitation bubble, Ultrason. Sonochem. 56 (2019) 63–76. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2019.03.019.<br>
[52]	B. Han, J. Chen, Z.H. Shen, J. Lu, X.W. Ni, Investigation of the wedge-shaped propelled surface for laser propulsion in water environment, Opt. Laser Technol. 43 (2011) 604–608. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.optlastec.2010.08.008.<br>
[53]	E.A. Brujan, H. Takahira, T. Ogasawara, Planar jets in collapsing cavitation bubbles, Exp. Therm. Fluid Sci. 101 (2019) 48–61. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.expthermflusci.2018.10.007.<br>
[54]	E.A. Brujan, Y. Matsumoto, Shock wave emission from a hemispherical cloud of bubbles in non-Newtonian fluids, J. Nonnewton. Fluid Mech. 204 (2014) 32–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jnnfm.2013.12.003.<br>
[55]	Y. Tomita, P.B. Robinson, R.P. Tong, J.R. Blake, Growth and collapse of cavitation bubbles near a curved rigid boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 466 (2002) 259–283. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112002001209.<br>
[56]	F.I. Azam, B. Karri, S.-W. Ohl, E. Klaseboer, B.C. Khoo, Dynamics of an oscillating bubble in a narrow gap, Phys. Rev. E. 88 (2013) 043006. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.88.043006.<br>
[57]	P.A. Quinto-Su, K.Y. Lim, C.D. Ohl, Cavitation bubble dynamics in microfluidic gaps of variable height, Phys. Rev. E - Stat. Nonlinear, Soft Matter Phys. 80 (2009) 047301. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.80.047301.<br>
[58]	Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, S. Li, The secondary Bjerknes force between two gas bubbles under dual-frequency acoustic excitation, Ultrason. Sonochem. 29 (2016) 129–145. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2015.08.022.<br>
[59]	P.A. Quinto-Su, C.-D.D. Ohl, Bubble cluster explosion, Phys. Fluids. 22 (2010) 091109. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.3483221.</p>
]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105375">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105375</a></p>
<h1 id="abstract">Abstract</h1>
<p>Herein, we investigated experimentally the dynamics of three laser-induced, same-sized, symmetrically aligned, and synchronized bubbles. Three synchronized laser beams split from the same beam using a Diffractive Optical Element splitter were focused on water, and then we obtained three bubbles. Another nanosecond laser pulse was used to probe the bubbles to obtain shadowgraphs. The exact delay of the excited and detected light was controlled using a delay generator. The results revealed that the maximum volumes of bubbles in arrays decrease as the normalized distance falls, while the lifetimes and translation increase. It was explained by the interaction between the acoustic radiation of bubbles and the surrounding bubbles. The shrinkage of linear bubble arrays exists an anomaly. The center bubbles were stretched, to ellipsoid, stick, even fractured, by the peripheral bubbles. The closer they are, the more distinct is the above phenomenon. However, when the normalized distance was sufficiently small, instead of being stretched, the center bubbles were compressed to disk shape and thus shrank with the whole array. Finally, the dependence of the distance on the energy transfer of the bubble system is also discussed.<br>
Keywords: Multi-bubbles dynamics, Laser-induced bubbles, Linear arrays, Non-spherical bubble, Holographic generation of bubbles</p>
<h1 id="i-introduction">I. Introduction</h1>
<p>Cavitation is an important phase-transition phenomenon in many fields, such as acoustics, sonochemistry, medicine, and hydraulics[1–8]. In the practice of these fields, cavitation is not isolated single one but tends to appear as filaments, streamers, clusters, and clouds in different styles of multiple bubbles groups. Studies on cavitation mainly focus on the deformation and mechanics revealed in the bubble dynamics and also the primary parameters of which are the phase and the size of bubbles. In a tiny region of the bubble groups, every two adjacent bubbles usually have similar phases and sizes [1,9,10]. In this respect, it is thus critical to clarify the interaction among the same-sized and synchronized multiple bubbles.</p>
<p>Many previous studies have focused on a single bubble, which assumes that the individual bubble behaviors are independent of the groups. The dynamics of a single bubble has been studied extensively for many years. For instance, Rayleigh, Plesset, Gilmore, and Keller studied the aspects of a single spherical bubble and developed the corresponding mathematical models[11–18]. On the other hand, in the studies of bubble groups, it was assumed that all bubbles followed the Rayleigh-Plesset model. In this case, these bubbles oscillate with the driving acoustic fields. Moreover, the natural frequency of bubble groups is lower than that of a single bubble. In the center of bubble groups, there exists energy accumulation and radiates high-intensity noise. When generated near the rigid boundary, bubble groups keep stationary for a while and then move toward the rigid boundary[7,18–27].</p>
<p>In fact, each bubble in the bubble groups is not independent. Thus the investigations on the interaction between two bubbles are significant because such studies can provide a valuable basis for multiple bubbles. Shima, Prosperetti, Mettin, Harkin, Fujikawa, Lauternborn, B.C.Khoo, Ohl explored two bubbles experimentally and theoretically based on the hypothesis of bubbles keeping spherical[28–37]. Consequently, it was noted that two synchronized bubbles with similar sizes usually attract each other and form jets towards each other in their shrink phase, and they have a longer lifetime. Nonetheless, when bubble pairs only have one pair of interactions, while bubbles in groups usually have several adjacent bubbles to interact with. Furthermore, the exact mechanism of interaction among multiple (i.e., three or more ) bubbles remains elusive[1,38]. However, the studies of bubble arrays have partially solved this problem.</p>
<p>Elsewhere, J.P.Dear and J.E.Field created static tension bubbles in gelatin, to study the reaction of acoustic pulse on the bubble arrays[39,40]. Nicolas Bremond, Manish Arora, Claus-Dieter Ohl, and Detlef Lohse studied the interaction of inflatable bubble arrays generated from a rigid surface[41,42]. Quinto-Su, Claus-Dieter Ohl focused laser modified by a spatial light modulator(SLM) on a liquid gap clamped by glass slides, to obtain quasi-two-dimensional bubble arrays. The studies indicated that, for a specific bubble, its adjacent bubbles modify its ambient pressure, and thereby mutually screen the pressure from the further position at the direction of the adjacent bubble[40,43]. The inner bubbles are confined by adjacent bubbles in the array dimensions. Their dynamics are primarily controlled by the reaction of adjacent bubbles and the free dimension. On the other hand, the peripheral bubbles are minimally confined, and their lifetimes are close to the isolated single bubble. Hence, the bubbles located centrally live most. Then the arrays collapse with a time sequence from outer to inner.</p>
<p>In general, three bubbles should receive more attention due to their high observability caused by a little amount, and high representativeness of mutual interaction from multiple adjacent bubbles. Siew -Wan Ohl, Lup Wai Chew, B.C.Khoo, and A.M.Zhang studied the dynamics of arrays of three bubbles generated by electric sparks in the free domain[34,36,44]. When the distances between synchronized bubbles are large, the center bubble will split when collapse, and each part will join with the verge bubbles, whereas three bubbles will join directly in the small distance case. The generated time and size influence the direction and style of bubble collapse. However, they did not control the position and energy of the exciting sources orderly. The dependence of separate distance on the orderly arranged arrays of similar bubbles has yet to be fully revealed.</p>
<p>In this paper, the holographic generation of millimeter-sized bubbles in a three-dimensional water column is attained using a high-power laser with a splitter. We used three split laser beams to accurately generate synchronized bubbles, with strictly controlled initial phases and size. Herein we purposed to clarify the dynamics of linear arrays of same-sized and synchronized cavitation bubbles in a quasi-free domain. Note that this paper concentrates on the deformation, size, lifetime, and translation of three synchronized bubbles in uniform alignment at different separate distances, during the period from birth to collapse, of laser-induced cavitation bubbles, which differs from the investigations above. Our approach is suitable for 3D geometries and a rather high laser fluence, which previously were not available. Such a study is currently lacking, and thus there is an urgent need for this aspect to be probed.</p>
<p>This paper is structured as follows. The second chapter introduces the experimental arrangement and the parameters of measurement. Relevant experimental results are presented in Chapter 3. In this chapter, the dynamics of multiple bubbles in the first oscillation period are analyzed. Then in a new chapter, some further discussions on the experiments are stated. Finally, minimum conclusions are provided.</p>
<h1 id="ii-experimental-setup">II. Experimental setup</h1>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="1"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr1.jpg" alt="fig1" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 1. Experimental arrangement for shadowgraphy of laser-induced multiple cavitation bubbles.</p>
<p>The experimental arrangement employed in this study for investigating the dynamics of laser-induced three symmetrically aligned in-phase bubbles is depicted in Figure 1.</p>
<p>To generate cavitation bubbles, a pulsed Nd:YAG laser generator (wavelength:1064nm; maximum energy:1J; pulse duration:10ns) was employed. The single laser pulse energy ranges from 100mJ to 1J. The fluctuations of the laser energy are approximately ±5%. Additionally, a beam splitter was utilized to split the pulse into two parts. Of which one part was reflected in an energy meter to monitor the incident pulse energy, while the other part was modulated into three beams using a triple-spot splitter DOE (Diffractive Optical Element; Holo/Or TS-245-I-Y-A). These three beams were aligned in the same vertical plane. Three mirrors were utilized to reflect these beams to an aplanat (f =30mm). The three reflecting spots aligned in the intersection of the incident plane, and also the plane in which the reflected laser and alignment bubbles were. Afterward, the aplanat lens was used for focusing on smaller spots to obtain regular bubbles. Hence, three pulse beams were focused and aligned on the focal plane. At these three focal points, deionized water was broken down in the water tank (fused silica, 50mm* 50mm * 50mm). Furthermore, plasma was generated, which then evolved into bubbles. We can obtain one or two bubbles by blocking certain beams. During the experiments, we set the different angles of the three incident beams, and the different distance between the mirrors to get different distances of the foci.</p>
<p>To visualize the fast process of bubble oscillation, we used a single frame CCD(Imi,imc7017g) combined with a short duration laser (Nd:YAG, wavelength = 1064nm, pulse duration = 2.5 ns). The probe laser propagates through the KTP frequency doubling crystal, and then the 1064nm pulse is transformed into a 532nm pulse. The new probe pulse beam was decayed and expanded through the aperture and the collimating expanding lens system. Afterward, the pulse beam which carries the information of bubbles propagates in the water and then approaching the CCD camera. The detection light was perpendicular to the exciting laser and the bubble line. A delay generator (Stanford Research Systems Inc., DG535) was utilized to trigger the CCD camera and lasers. By reading the time delay between the plasma flash and probe pulse, which was detected by a photodiode, we obtained the exact time of the image which was gathered using the CCD.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="2"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr2.jpg" alt="fig2" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 2. A schematic description of the bubble setups, including the definitions of several essential parameters. The left upper frame shows the maximum radius of an isolated single bubble. The red dash is an outline circle. The shadow area can be used to calculate the radius, which is obtained by the collapse time with the K-M model. The left lower frame shows the initial breakdown spots when γ=0.45. The mean value of the yellow and green length is the initial distance of bubbles, D0. The right frame is a typical image in γ=0.8. The red dash is the minimum bounding rectangle of the verge bubbles, whereas, the blue one is the minimum bounding rectangle of the center bubble. The green line is the B-verge-outer, while the yellow line is B-verge-inner. The pale blue line is the minor axis of the center bubble, B-center, while the orange line is the major axes, and also it can be defined as 2*A in different bubbles. D refers to the exact distance that is not shown in the scheme. It is a mean value of the distance of the centroids, which are the intersection points of the three cross in the frame.</p>
<p>Here, parameters that we focused on include the size and distance of bubbles. The radii of bubbles at a specific time, R, are obtained by the shadows, whose area is πR2. Given is the maximum radius of bubbles R0 in a single oscillation process. The initial distance D0 is the mean value of the distances between each two adjacent breakdown spots, as depicted in Figure 2. For normalization, a dimensionless parameter γ is defined as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>γ</mi><mo>=</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>D</mi><mn>0</mn></msub><mrow><mn>2</mn><msub><mi>R</mi><mn>0</mn></msub></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">\gamma = \frac { D _ { 0 } } { 2 R _ { 0 } }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.625em;vertical-align:-0.19444em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.05556em;">γ</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.3335309999999998em;vertical-align:-0.44509999999999994em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8884309999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.655em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:-0.00773em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">0</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.4101em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:-0.02778em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">0</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.44509999999999994em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span><br>
(1.1)</p>
<p>Other important parameters in the bubble dynamics A, B are shown in Figure 2. Because of the interaction between bubbles, they lose their sphericities during the oscillation. Considering two-dimensional patterns, A is the semi-major axis of the bubble in the photos, while B is the semi-minor axis. However, the profile of the bubble is usually irregular. We treat the horizontal axis of the minimum bounding rectangle as the major axis of the bubble. Moreover, the distance from the centroid to the outer horizontal side of the rectangle is defined as B-outer, so does the B-inner. Two verge/peripheral bubbles average a general A, B-outer, and B-inner. Furthermore, B of the center bubble is the average of the distances from the centroid to the top and bottom.</p>
<p>To understand the deformation in the whole process, a normalized parameter C, that is, the degree of circularity is introduced[45]. It is defined as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>C</mi><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>m</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>t</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>o</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>a</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>a</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>e</mi><mi>q</mi><mi>u</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>v</mi><mi>a</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>n</mi><mi>t</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>c</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>c</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>e</mi></mrow><mrow><mi>p</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mi>i</mi><mi>m</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>t</mi><mi>e</mi><mi>r</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>o</mi><mi>f</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>b</mi><mi>u</mi><mi>b</mi><mi>b</mi><mi>l</mi><mi>e</mi></mrow></mfrac><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mrow><mn>2</mn><msqrt><mrow><mi>π</mi><mi>S</mi></mrow></msqrt></mrow><msub><mi>P</mi><mi>b</mi></msub></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">C=\frac {perimeter-of-area-equivalent-circle }{perimeter-of-bubble} =\frac { 2 \sqrt { \pi S } } { P _ { b } }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.68333em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4133239999999998em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322159999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">m</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">o</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.10764em;">f</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">u</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.01968em;">l</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">m</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">o</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.10764em;">f</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">q</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">u</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">v</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.01968em;">l</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">n</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="mbin mtight">−</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">i</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.01968em;">l</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">e</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4974629999999998em;vertical-align:-0.4508599999999999em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.046603em;"><span style="top:-2.655em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">P</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.3448em;"><span style="top:-2.3487714285714287em;margin-left:-0.13889em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">b</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.15122857142857138em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span><span class="mord sqrt mtight"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322900000000001em;"><span class="svg-align" style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord mtight" style="padding-left:0.833em;"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">π</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.05764em;">S</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.89229em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="hide-tail mtight" style="min-width:0.853em;height:1.08em;"><svg width='400em' height='1.08em' viewBox='0 0 400000 1080' preserveAspectRatio='xMinYMin slice'><path d='M95,702c-2.7,0,-7.17,-2.7,-13.5,-8c-5.8,-5.3,-9.5,
-10,-9.5,-14c0,-2,0.3,-3.3,1,-4c1.3,-2.7,23.83,-20.7,67.5,-54c44.2,-33.3,65.8,
-50.3,66.5,-51c1.3,-1.3,3,-2,5,-2c4.7,0,8.7,3.3,12,10s173,378,173,378c0.7,0,
35.3,-71,104,-213c68.7,-142,137.5,-285,206.5,-429c69,-144,104.5,-217.7,106.5,
-221c5.3,-9.3,12,-14,20,-14H400000v40H845.2724s-225.272,467,-225.272,467
s-235,486,-235,486c-2.7,4.7,-9,7,-19,7c-6,0,-10,-1,-12,-3s-194,-422,-194,-422
s-65,47,-65,47z M834 80H400000v40H845z'/></svg></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.10770999999999997em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.4508599999999999em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span><br>
(1.2)</p>
<p>where S denotes the area of the bubble in the photos, which has a perimeter Pb. The numerator of this equation means the perimeter or circumference of a circle, which has an area equal to that of a bubble with perimeter Pb. In this case, a perfect circle has a C= 1. The more the bubble shape varies from being a circle, the smaller the circularity value.</p>
<p>To track the relative location changing of bubbles, a non-dimensional distance   is introduced. It is defined as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><msup><mi>D</mi><mo mathvariant="normal">′</mo></msup><mo>=</mo><mfrac><mi>D</mi><msub><mi>D</mi><mn>0</mn></msub></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">{D&#x27;}=\frac {D}{D_0}</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.751892em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.751892em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">′</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.317431em;vertical-align:-0.44509999999999994em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.872331em;"><span style="top:-2.655em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:-0.02778em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight">0</span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">D</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.44509999999999994em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span>(1.3)</p>
<p>where D represents the distance in a certain time, while D0 represents the initial distance between the verge bubbles to the center bubble as introduced in Figure 2.</p>
<p>In these experiments, the maximum bubble radii were obtained in single spherical bubble experiments in the bulk of water before the bubble arrays experiments with the same laser energy [33,34]. We recorded the oscillation of single bubbles in bulk water as well as measured their collapse time. The results of this experiment concurred with the radius in the Keller-Miksis model. The time of collapse the photos recorded fluctuated about ±5%. Thus, the ideal maximum radius of a single oscillating bubble in bulk water with a notation R0 is characterized by the mid-value of collapse time [46]. Compared with the results from the area of shadows in the shadowgraph, which is <span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mo>(</mo><msqrt><mrow><mi>max</mi><mo>⁡</mo><mo>(</mo><mtext>Area</mtext><mo>)</mo></mrow></msqrt><mo>)</mo><mi mathvariant="normal">/</mi><mi>π</mi></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">( \sqrt { \max ( \text {Area} ) } ) / \pi</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.24em;vertical-align:-0.30499999999999994em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord sqrt"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.935em;"><span class="svg-align" style="top:-3.2em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3.2em;"></span><span class="mord" style="padding-left:1em;"><span class="mop">max</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord text"><span class="mord">Area</span></span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.8950000000000005em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3.2em;"></span><span class="hide-tail" style="min-width:1.02em;height:1.28em;"><svg width='400em' height='1.28em' viewBox='0 0 400000 1296' preserveAspectRatio='xMinYMin slice'><path d='M263,681c0.7,0,18,39.7,52,119c34,79.3,68.167,
158.7,102.5,238c34.3,79.3,51.8,119.3,52.5,120c340,-704.7,510.7,-1060.3,512,-1067
c4.7,-7.3,11,-11,19,-11H40000v40H1012.3s-271.3,567,-271.3,567c-38.7,80.7,-84,
175,-136,283c-52,108,-89.167,185.3,-111.5,232c-22.3,46.7,-33.8,70.3,-34.5,71
c-4.7,4.7,-12.3,7,-23,7s-12,-1,-12,-1s-109,-253,-109,-253c-72.7,-168,-109.3,
-252,-110,-252c-10.7,8,-22,16.7,-34,26c-22,17.3,-33.3,26,-34,26s-26,-26,-26,-26
s76,-59,76,-59s76,-60,76,-60z M1001 80H40000v40H1012z'/></svg></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.30499999999999994em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord">/</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">π</span></span></span></span> , small differences can be ignored. The initial distance of bubbles, D0, was extracted by the earliest frame below 100ns, while plasma is recombining and converting to vapor[47].</p>
<p>Keller-Miksis(K-M) model is a relatively complete model, describing the oscillation of single spherical bubbles. It takes into account the surface tension, viscosity, compressibility and gas inside the bubble[17], reading</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mi>R</mi><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>¨</mo></mover><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><msup><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mrow><mn>3</mn><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mi>ρ</mi></mfrac><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mi>R</mi><mrow><mi>ρ</mi><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mfrac><mrow><mi>d</mi><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub></mrow><mrow><mi>d</mi><mi>t</mi></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) R \ddot { R } + \frac { 3 } { 2 } \dot { R } ^ { 2 } ( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { 3 c } ) = ( 1 + \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) \frac { p _ { 1 } } { \rho } + \frac { R } { \rho c } \frac { d p _ { 1 } } { d t }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.16666em;">¨</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.26519em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.845108em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8141079999999999em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.519241em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4133239999999998em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.872331em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322159999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span> ,	(1.4)</p>
<p>where R denotes the bubble’s radius while ρ is the density of the liquid. Besides, the speed of sound in the liquid, C, is assumed to be a constant. The gas inside the bubble obeys the van der Waals law. Combined with the ambient pressure pstat, the pressure at the bubble wall p1 can be given as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mi>R</mi><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>¨</mo></mover><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mn>3</mn><mn>2</mn></mfrac><msup><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>−</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mrow><mn>3</mn><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mo>(</mo><mn>1</mn><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mi>C</mi></mfrac><mo>)</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub><mi>ρ</mi></mfrac><mo>+</mo><mfrac><mi>R</mi><mrow><mi>ρ</mi><mi>c</mi></mrow></mfrac><mfrac><mrow><mi>d</mi><msub><mi>p</mi><mn>1</mn></msub></mrow><mrow><mi>d</mi><mi>t</mi></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) R \ddot { R } + \frac { 3 } { 2 } \dot { R } ^ { 2 } ( 1 - \frac { \dot { R } } { 3 c } ) = ( 1 + \frac { \dot { R } } { C } ) \frac { p _ { 1 } } { \rho } + \frac { R } { \rho c } \frac { d p _ { 1 } } { d t }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.16666em;">¨</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.26519em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.845108em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8141079999999999em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.383133em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">3</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">1</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.519241em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.038133em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.07153em;">C</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord accent mtight"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-2.7em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-2.9523300000000003em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;"><span class="mtight">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.4133239999999998em;vertical-align:-0.481108em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.872331em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">c</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.481108em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9322159999999999em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.31731428571428577em;"><span style="top:-2.357em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">1</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.143em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span>(1.5)</p>
<p>where Rn is the equilibrium radius of the bubble, pv is the vapor pressure, μ is the dynamic viscosity, and σ is the surface tension coefficient of the liquid, and p(t) is the pressure of sound fields. Moreover, b is the van der Waals parameter given as 0.0016, while κ is the polytropic exponent denoted as 4/3. The concrete data used in calculations were retrieved from the references[46,48].</p>
<p>Herein, five groups of γ( 0.45=1.35mm/(2<em>1.5 mm), 0.80=2.40 mm /(2</em>1.5 mm), 1.0=3.0 mm /(2<em>1.5 mm), 1.47=2.94 mm /(2</em>1 mm), and 1.93=3.85 mm /(2*1 mm) ) were employed for experimental studies. The aforementioned cases represent that the ideal geometry of adjacent bubbles is mutually covered, squeezed, touched, about, and aloof. Lastly, more than 20 photos were taken every 5μs in the whole progress to assess the multi-bubbles dynamics for given conditions.</p>
<h1 id="iii-experimental-results">III. Experimental results</h1>
<p>In this section, experimental results of typical cases and their mechanisms are interpreted based on the shadowgraph and the simplified explanation of bubble-bubble interaction. In particular, this only considers the effect of an acoustic pressure wave of a bubble radiated on the other bubbles[49–51]. The dominant parameter in this work is γ, the non-dimension distance between two adjacent bubbles, which is defined in formula 1.1.</p>
<p>Figures 3, 5, 7, 9, 11 illustrates selected frames of the experimental photos of the dynamics of three symmetrical aligned in-phase bubbles for five typical distances. The main process of Figures 3-12 can be summarized as follows in terms of different values of γ and the relationship of the geometries of adjacent bubbles when they expand in isolation:</p>
<p>Case 1: Large γ (γ=1.93 in Figure 3), causes the isolated maximized geometries to leave each other. Two diameter-equaled space separated the bubbles at the maximum. They exhibited the weakest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 2: Large γ (γ=1.47 in Figure 5), causes the isolated maximized geometries to near to each other. Two radius-equaled space separated the bubbles at the maximum. They elucidated the second weakest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 3: Medium γ (γ=1.0 in Figure 7), causes the isolated maximized geometries to touch each other. The bubbles contacted to each other at the maximum radii and showed intermediate interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 4: Little γ (γ=0.80 in Figure 9), causes the isolated maximized geometries to squeeze each other. The bubbles contacted to each other before the maximum radii and had the second strongest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<p>Case 5: Little γ (γ= 0.45 in Figure 11), causes the isolated maximized geometries to cover each other. The bubbles were quite close to each other, even have limited the early expanding significantly. In this case, bubbles had the strongest interaction in the experimental cases we have taken.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="3"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr3.jpg" alt="fig3" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 3. Case 1: Large γ (γ=1.93) experimental results with the weakest interaction.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="4"><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr4.jpg" alt="fig4" loading="lazy"></figure>
<p>Figure 4. Parameters in Case 1.</p>
<p>In the figures above and below(Figure 3 - Figure13), t is the exact time and T0 is the first oscillation period of bubbles in isolation, while T = t/T0 is the normalized time. Usually, an isolated bubble expands before T = 0.5, reaching its maximum at T=0.5, then shrinks and eventually collapses at T = 1.</p>
<p>Figures 3 and 4 display the results of Case 1, γ = 1.93. Big initial separations induce weak bubble interactions. In Figure 3, the first frame reflects the starting of bubbles. The morphologies of bubbles nuclei are revealed to be similar to that of plasma calculated using a transient coupling model [47], which implies that this starting of bubbles follows the dynamics of the laser-induced plasma. Furthermore, based on the time series diagram, the deformation of the bubbles is primarily influenced by the initial shape. During the expansion period, the shadow area in frames 2, 3, 4 on the upper column, the volume of the center bubble was slightly smaller than that of the verge bubbles. This signifies that the phase of the center bubble is slightly delayed, and thus the verge bubbles reach the maximum bubble radius before the center one. Here, the phase was noted as the relative position of the bubbles' state of motion in a period， [34]. If the period of periodic motion is extended, the time when a bubble reaches a certain phase is delayed. Here, phase delayed means that the period of the first oscillation is extended. In shrinkage, the phase of the verge bubbles also precedes the center bubble. The interactions caused by the pressure and tension waves of bubbles radiation are gradually becoming apparent. As indicated in the first frame of the bottom column, the bubbles elongated, and the outer edge of the verge bubbles get flattened and then shrink faster than the inner edge. Subsequently, as shown in the second frame of the bottom column, the verge bubbles produce jets pointing toward the center bubble, which remains a larger volume. In the third frame of the bottom column, the verge bubbles collapse and produce shock waves, but the center bubble survives and continues shrinking. Finally, the center bubble collapse after the fourth frame. Whilst, the positions of rebound verge bubbles move towards the center.</p>
<p>Figure 4 depicts the normalized Rs and axes of bubbles and circularity over time. The distribution of Rs is flatter and wider compared to the K-M curve. This implies that the development of bubbles is inhibited. During the interactions of the bubbles, the energy of each bubble, which is converted to potential energy, is less than that of single bubbles so that the bubbles cannot reach its R0, and thus their phase is delayed. Here the phase delay was followed by a decrease of maximum radii due to the limited bubble energy. The center bubble was affected by two verge bubbles simultaneously, while the two verge bubbles were only affected by the center bubble because of the screen effect[40,41]. Therefore, the center bubble is more significantly inhibited, indicating a smaller Rmax and more phase delay than the verge bubbles. During the expansion, the A and B axes differed slightly. However, when the bubbles in both positions enter the shrinking phase, the negative radiation pressure will stretch the other bubbles, mainly on the B axis, and thereby elongating the B axis. Remarkably, the center bubble was stretched most, and hence its A and B axes were longer than that of the verge bubbles. The B-inner and B-outer based on the minimum bounding rectangle can not accurately describe the deformation of the verge bubbles due to the concave deformation. From the image of C, the C of verge bubbles become smaller at the end of the shrinkage, that is, at T= 1.05. On the other hand, the center bubble loses its C at T = 0.8 due to the stretching. Conclusively, the motion of bubbles in Case 1 is similar to that of an isolated single bubble, but the phase is slightly prolonged, the maximum radii are slightly smaller, and deformation occurs before the collapse.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr5.jpg" alt="fig5" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 5. Case 2: Large γ (γ =1.47), experimental results with the second weakest interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr6.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 6. Parameters in Case 2.</p>
<p>Figure 5 and 6 present the results of Case 2, γ = 1.47. Overall, the result was similar to that of Case 1. However, the smaller spacing between the bubbles enhanced their interaction, while some effects might be more pronounced for the multi-bubble system. The initial phase exhibited very little impact, like the second frame. The phase delay was more pronounced than Case 1. In addition, the inhibition of phase due to the interaction was similar to that of Case1. Comparing the four frames of third and fourth in the bottom columns of Figures 3 and 5, the collapse time of the two kinds of bubbles in Case 2 was delayed, with a higher time difference between the center and verge bubbles. The phase delay of the center bubble was apparent due to the dual inhibition of two verge bubbles. Thus, the T of stretching and collapse was delayed.</p>
<p>From the Rs graph, the curves of Case 2 are broader and lower than that of Case 1. The rebound of Case 2 is at T &gt; 1.1, while that of Case 1 is at T ≈ 1.1. Additionally, the maximum value of R in Case 2 was slightly lower than that of Case 1, and the reaching time is also delayed, which is the phase delay caused by inhibition. The difference between center and verge Rs also expands. From the axes graph, A, B, and R of verge bubbles are synchronized to reach the maximum and then contract, reach the minimum, and then rebound. On the other hand, A and B of the center bubble is synchronized with R during the expansion phase and is smaller than the A and B of verge bubbles. Thus, A-center is flatter and broader than axes of verge bubbles. The B-center separates from the other axis curves at T=0.65 and remains continuously high until it decreases after T = 1.0. This signifies the center bubble of Case 2 is elongated in the vertical direction.</p>
<p>Compared to Case 1, the bubble deformation in Case 2 was more pronounced. The C of verge bubbles rapidly decrease in the late stage of shrinkage, T = 1.0, due to the jets penetrating the bubbles. The rebound period also maintains a smaller C due to multi-bubble disturbance and unstable processes. The C of the elongated center bubble starts to decline slowly at T = 0.65, and eventually decreases sharply during the collapse phase. Finally, compared with Case 1, the overall deformation is more prominent, and the deformation time T is also advanced.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr7.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 7. Case 3: Medium γ (γ = 1.0) experimental results with intermediate interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr8.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 8. Parameters in Case 3.</p>
<p>Figures 7 and 8 show the results of Case 3, γ = 1.0. The interactions were more evident due to a closer spacing. As shown in the third frame of Figure 7, the expansion of the center bubble is inhibited. Consequently, the inner edges of the verge bubbles get flattened. Therefore, the centroids of verge bubbles form an offset due to the interaction of push. The fourth frame revealed that the verge bubbles reach near their maximum radii, while the phase of the center bubble lags far behind, and also its radius does not reach the maximum. Furthermore, both kinds of bubbles deform significantly, whereas the opposite surfaces get more flattened. As a result, the centroids of verge bubbles move towards the center bubble due to the shape change. As indicated in the fifth frame, when the center bubble reaches near the maximum radius, the verge bubbles begin to shrink. Between the fourth and fifth frames, there is no contact between the three bubbles, and there exist two thick gaps of water layers, the length of which are in the range of 0.3R0 - 0.4R0. Consequently, the verge bubbles shrink and form a stretch against the center bubble, as depicted in frame 6. Moreover, the verge bubbles form jets from the outer boundary towards the center bubble. The phase difference between bubbles gradually accumulates under the influence of the interaction. The center bubble continues to grow in the vertical direction, while the horizontal shrinkage is approximately synchronized with the verge bubbles, as viewed in frames 6, 7. Lastly, the jets penetrate the verge bubbles vertically. Then the verge bubbles collapse and rebound while the center bubble collapses and rebounds horizontally (as shown in frame 8). The collapse times are delayed compared to that of Case 2.</p>
<p>Figure 8 shows the normalized radii, axes, and circularity over time of Case 3. The initial expansion of bubbles follows the K-M model. When the pressure waves induced by expansion start to affect each other, the expansion is slowed down by a decrease in the differential pressure between inside and outside. As indicated in the radii graph, the R curves were clearly no longer symmetric curves of T = Tx (in K-M, Tx= 0.5). They become smoother with the growth of span. The maximum bubble radii that can be reached by the inner and outer bubbles are larger than that of K-M. The verge bubbles reached their maximum R at T = 0.5, while the center bubble reached its maximum R at T = 0.6. Both the center and verge bubbles maintained stable and maximum for a longer time duration significantly. This corresponds to the interaction of the tension waves generated by the shrinkage.</p>
<p>Overall, the axes of verge bubbles changed similarly to R. This is also consistent with the higher C, which means the bubbles have better circularity. The A and B of the center bubble were smaller than those of verge bubbles in the expanding stage. However, the center bubble begins to change apparently at T = 0.6 when it reached the maximum radius. The deceleration of A-center was slower, and its height was higher than the axes of verge bubbles because there are no adhesions, and also the effect of the tension wave is greater. The B-center continues to increase linearly to approximately T = 1.1 and then plummets due to the occurrence of collapse. This turn occurs faster and later than that of Case 2. The B-verge -outer is higher than the B-verge-inner, which indicates that the centroids of verge bubbles move towards the center, and their parts closer to the center bubble are wider. Finally, the deformation of the center bubble, which the A and B show, represent in C as a gradual smooth reduction starting at T = 0.6 and reaching a minimum at collapse.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr9.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 9. Case 4: Little γ (γ = 0.80) experimental results with the second strongest interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr10.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 10. Parameters in Case 4.</p>
<p>Figures 9and 10 show the results of Case4, γ = 0.8. From the second frame of the upper column, the initial evolution of the bubbles was still spherical. The phases of bubbles become different after the bubbles are affected by the pressure wave induced by other bubbles. In frame 3, the verge bubbles are significantly larger than the center bubble. This may be attributed to the effect of the inhibition described above. Thus the center and verge bubbles form a more evident phase difference. Whilst, the bubble expansions are inhibited, the contacted parts get flattened, and bubbles push each other. In frame 4, the verge bubbles begin to shrink. Under the combination of hydrostatic pressure, tensile force, and internal bubble pressure, the center bubble maintains maximum for a longer time than in K-M. Because of this mutual stretching, the space between the bubbles is reduced. In the frames of the bottom column, the center bubbles shrink but are also stretched by the verge bubbles to form a distinctive cylinder structure. Consequently, the opposite surfaces get flattened, while the vertical sides deform from the horizontal symmetry axis as well as the middle position of the vertical sides. In the second frame of the bottom column, distinct water films form between the bubbles. The verge bubbles collapse inward partly due to the jets. The horizontal shrinkage of the center bubbles was substantial. The opposite sides of the verge bubbles to the center bubble are stretched by the center bubble. The closer to the vertical symmetry axis and the center bubble, the slower the phase is. This phase delay creates inward jets on the outer boundaries. In frame 3 of the lower column, the jets from the verge bubble penetrates their bubbles and shoot into the center bubble, which continues to shrink, necking to a remarkable hourglass. In the later stage, the center bubble may collapse at the waist of the hourglass. In frame 4 below, the verge bubble collapses completely, and their residual gas is mixed with the residual gas from the center bubble. The phase of the center part of the center bubble is more advanced, resulting in rebound earlier than the other part. However, due to the unstable of residual gas and water, the center bubble collapses to a complex state. The time of jets forming and collapse was delayed compared to that of Case 3. In cases where γ is small enough, bubbles may develop an outspread adhesion in the opposite centers during oscillation. Although significant boundary gaps can still be observed, as disclosed in frame 7. Under this circumstance, when we processed the images, we connected the closest two points of two gaps, and deemed the lines as the boundaries of bubbles, without considering the influence of jets on R in the three-dimensional scale. Then we calculate the parameters of bubbles as mentioned in the experimental setup.</p>
<p>Figure 10 outlines the normalized radii, axes, and circularity over time of Case 4. The R curves were smoother with the loss of symmetry. After reaching their maximum value, Rs changed slowly and remain at a relatively high level. The initial stage of expansion was slightly different than that of K-M. As the pressure waves from the other bubbles reached the exact bubble, its expansion was gradually inhibited. The center bubble was affected by double interactions, and thus its inhibition was bigger, which leads to its more phase delay. Additionally, the R of the center bubble was smaller than that of verge bubbles in the expansion, but bigger in shrinkage. The verge bubbles reached their maximum radii within a short time after T = 0.5 and then declined slowly. On the other hand, the center bubble reached its maximum radius near T = 0.8, and then decline slower than the verge bubbles. Here, the difference between Rs and K-M was bigger than in Case 3.</p>
<p>The B of the center bubble in the axes graph of Figure 8 reveals a sharp contraction at the end of shrinkage. However, in Figure 10, it has only two stages namely growth and stabilization. The stable stage extends to the right of the figure until the cavitation bubble is broken. Thus we can treat it as the turn we mentioned in Case 2 and 3, of this curve moved towards a positive direction. This is because after the bubble is pulled into a cylinder, its shrinkage is mainly reflected as an hourglass shrinkage, and in deformation. After fracturing at the waist, the minimum bounding rectangle of the remnant center bubble changed slightly. The B-inner of the verge bubbles was more affected, and therefore smaller than the B-outer. In comparison, the difference between B-verge-inner and B-verge-outer become bigger than that of Case 3. This suggests that the centroid translation caused by the deformation gets more evident. The As of the center and verge bubbles change synchronously because the tension at the opposite and contact surfaces is balanced. The contraction did not occur at the width of the minimum bounding rectangle, and thus As may exhibit high value and decline slowly. The C of Case 4 starts to decline slowly at T = 0.2, while in Case 3 it is at T = 0.6. This was caused by the squeeze. Cs remain high during the expansion period. The C-center was smaller because the center bubbles are squeezed greater. When shrink, the shape of the verge bubbles is flattened by the jets, and the center bubble necks to an hourglass. Their Cs gradually get smaller and decrease violently as the shrinkage progresses. Meanwhile, the verge bubbles deform violently, resulting in a smaller C-verge.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr11.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 11. Case 5: Little γ (γ = 0.45) experimental results with the strongest interaction.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr12.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 12. Parameters in Case 5.</p>
<p>Figures 11 and 12 show Case 5, γ = 0.45. The second and third frames on the top column are the early stage of bubble expansion. Bubbles got flat at the opposite position to each other while the other positions expand as normal. The opposite surfaces got nearly parallel. The closer to the vertical symmetric axis, the earlier the surface becomes flat. The length of parallel surfaces increases over time before reaching the maximum. In the fourth frame on the top column, the center bubble grows to a cylinder because of the squeezing of two verge bubbles; the verge bubbles grew like straight mouth bowls with a round bottom at the same time. Water films persisted between the bubbles.</p>
<p>The contact surfaces continue expanding due to the increased pressure difference caused by the bubble interaction. The verge bubbles evolved into an open bowl, while the side of the center bubble looks like a hyperbola. The central part of the center bubble started to shrink as the internal pressure was released. The squeezing caused the parts to move out of phase, and the bubbles were unable to reach their maximum radii at the same time. In the vertical parts of the bubbles, the phase was more advanced, whereas, in the second frame in the lower column, the upper and lower bubbles form jets in the vertical symmetrical axis. Additionally, we can still observe the delineation of bubbles. Since the phase at the contact parts was delayed, the bubbles as a whole exhibited a cross shape shrinkage. The phase of the non-contact parts of the center bubble was later than that of the verge bubbles due to the double action of the other two bubbles. The cross shrinkage is mainly reflected in the vertical direction. The last frame indicated that the bubbles finally collapse vertically and radiate shockwaves outwards, ending up a dish-shaped remnant. The center bubble was smaller than the verge bubbles in the expansion but bigger in the shrinkage. Overall, the lifetimes of the three bubbles were nearly equal, and being longer than those in Case 4.</p>
<p>Figure 12 shows the normalized radii, axes, and circularity over the normalized time of Case 5. The Rs still obeyed the K-M model of isolated single bubble expansion in the early stage of cavitation. When the pressure fields of bubbles induced begin to influence each other, the pressure waves increase the external pressure and hence reduced the pressure difference. Thus, the progress of R was inhibited. The asymmetry of R curves gets more evident. When expanded, the center bubble was subjected to the pressure wave of both verge bubbles. Its external pressure is higher than the others, the pressure difference is less, and the inhibition is larger, while the verge bubbles are only affected by the pressure of the center bubble due to the isolation effect of the center bubble, and also receive less inhibition. Therefore, the verge bubbles reach the maximum radii before the center bubble, but later than that of an isolated single bubble in the first oscillation period. The difference between maximum Rs of the center bubble and that of the verge bubbles reached was small. Besides, they are all smaller than those in the K-M model and Case 4. Meanwhile, Rs changes more slightly than in Case 4. In the early shrink stage, the internal pressure was lower than the external pressure. Bubbles radiate a pulling force pointing to itself. Therefore, the difference between the internal and external pressure of other bubbles become less, and the oscillation gets inhibition. Bubbles shrink synchronously in the vertical; thus, the difference between Rs of the center and verge bubbles are small. Generally, for the center bubble, the period was more extensive; the phase was delayed due to it receiving larger inhibition.</p>
<p>On the axes graph, we can observe the inhibitory effect more clearly. At the primary stage of the bubble, it expands rapidly. After the normalized length reaches about 0.3, the expansion slowed down significantly. Then Bs stabilizes near the maximum and slowly declines after reaching the maximum. The B-inners were more severely affected, which represents the length of the opposite surface to the centroids. When B-verge-inner +B-center = 0.9 = 2*γ, the edges of the isolated expanding bubbles should contact each other. However, we observed in the column above, that there was a presence of water film. The continuous growth of the short axis was accompanied by the displacement of the relative position of bubbles. The interaction between the bubbles forms a push that pushes the verge bubbles away from the center bubbles. As mentioned above, the center bubble is affected by two pressure fields, while the verge bubbles were affected by only one pressure field. Thus, B of the center bubble is smaller than that of the verge bubbles. In addition, the difference between B-verge-outer and B-verge-inner was more apparent than that of Case 4. This purports that the shift of verge bubble centroids is considerable while the mutual extension of the inter-bubble joints is stable.</p>
<p>Particularly, when T = 0.4, the Bs reach the maximum, as well the bubble distances, as denoted in Figure 11, upper frame 4. After this point, the bubble energy is released mainly through the mutual extension of the inter-bubble joints. Subsequently, As refers to the length of the joint, which appears a process of re-growth. In this re-growth progress, the As of center and verge bubbles change synchronously and reach their maximum at approximately T=0.8. However, there exists a small difference because the center bubble shrinks horizontally while the verge bubbles predominately shrink along the vertical direction. Hence, the axes cannot accurately describe the bowl-shaped deformation of verge bubbles and the hyperbolic deformation of the center bubble. Therefore, C becomes an excellent auxiliary parameter to describe the deformation. From the circularity graph in the upper column of Figure 12, it can be viewed that the beginning of the circularity loss is earlier than T=0.1. The deformation of the center bubble is more than that of verge bubbles. Then at T = 0.4, the C-center dropped a sudden. This progress corresponds to the mutual extension of the inter-bubble joints after the bubbles contact each other. The C flatten out when the R reaches the maximum, and rise due to the global shrinkage of the center bubble. Afterward, it declined after T = 1.0 because the vertical shrinkage of the center plays a significant role.</p>
<p><img src="https://ars.els-cdn.com/content/image/1-s2.0-S1350417720316795-gr13.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Figure 13. The normalized distance of different case. Little γ receives a greater push effect.</p>
<p>Figure 13 shows the results of normalized bubble distance,   over time in case 5.   can be used as a measure of the bubble interactions, while   = 1 represents the initial position of the bubble center. A bigger   indicates that the bubbles are far away from each other, whereas a smaller   means they are close to each other. Furthermore,   reflects the effect of bubbles radiated pressure waves on other bubbles. Also, it shows the movement of verge bubbles, while on the other hand, it reflects their deformation. If the proximal and distal ends are fixed, the deformation also changes the centroids. The flattening of the opposite surface of bubbles makes   smaller. Likewise, jets produced and penetrated inwards would also make   smaller. Here, the effects of these two factors are considered indiscriminately as the centroid distance change is caused by bubbles interaction.</p>
<p>Due to the geometrical attenuation of the radiated pressure waves, the closer the position is in the same direction of the assumed spherical bubble, the stronger is the sound pressure. The smaller the γ is, the larger the ratio of stress surface to radiation wave sphere is, and the more evident is the forced effect. Therefore, the smaller the γ is, the more apparent is the effect of the inter -bubble force. As shown in the graph, the smaller the γ is, then, the larger the maximum value of   is, the faster the  changes, and the later   reaches its maximum. This indicates that the closer the bubbles are to each other, the more energy is used to push the adjacent bubbles away. After   exceeds 1, the time of falling below 1 decreases with γ increasing. This means the bigger the γ is, the sooner it can stop pushing each other around and return to its original position. In the shrinking phase before T = 1.0, that is, none bubbles have rebounded, the smaller the γ is, the steeper the curve becomes. Thus it indicates that the larger the γ is, the greater the potential energy accumulated, the longer the acceleration distance is, and the faster the movement is. These also tell that the time duration of the negative pressure radiated by bubbles is broad enough to complete the process.</p>
<p>When γ = 1.93, the push between the bubbles is almost negligible. However, in the shrinking phase,   decreases, in part due to the proximity of bubbles, as well as the deformation caused by jets. In the rebound phase, the verge bubbles penetrated by jets rebound with movement inward, thus the   decreases.</p>
<p>In Case 2, γ = 1.47, it can be noted that the part above  =1 has a certain curvature. The push effect was greater than Case 1. Meanwhile, at the pull stage, the curve turns earlier.<br>
When γ = 1.0, the push and pull between bubbles were notable. The difference in the time phase between bubbles increases, while the center bubble collapses laterally in a stick shape with stable length. Moreover, the verge bubbles re-expanded in the direction of the jets,   decreases significantly.</p>
<p>In the case of γ = 0.8, 0.45, the push and pull between bubbles were more apparent. At the shrinking phase of Case 4, the center bubble collapsed in an hourglass shape. Also, it may disintegrate at the vertical center. Thereafter, the two separated parts will move outward and merge with verge bubbles, and then collapse near the position of verge bubbles. Therefore, in this case, the   is small but larger compared to that in case 3. On the other hand, in Case 5, center and verge bubbles collapsed in a disk-shape. The denominator of  ，D0， is little enough so that the change in the trend of   is not too obvious. Besides, the phase difference between center and verge bubbles was quite little at collapse, so that simultaneous collapse and rebounding does not occur.</p>
<h1 id="iv-discussion">IV. Discussion</h1>
<p>Bubbles can be treated as symmetrically aligned in-phase bubbles, taking into account the isolation effect and ignoring the small angular shifts in the arrangement between the bubbles. The behavior of bubbles at different positions can be approximated to different existing examples. For instance, the center bubble is restricted in two directions, and its oscillation is similar to that of a bubble between two parallel rigid boundaries. The verge bubbles, on the other hand, are inhibited in one direction and thus exhibit similar patterns as if they were bubbles near a rigid boundary. Jets are formed towards the center bubble during the shrinking phase. However, in the experiments, since the three laser beams are focused from the same lens, there is an inevitable focus shift at a larger incident angle at the time of breakdown. Thus the three points are not strictly linearly aligned but form a specific small angular offset. At this point, the interactions between the bubbles are different from the aforementioned analogy. The center bubble receives the action of bubbles on both sides, not in a straight line, but an angle. The behavior of center bubbles can be analogized to bubbles in different angular structures. In the experimental figures, the left and right boundaries of the center bubbles during the shrinking phase are not symmetrical. Notably, in Figures 9 and 11, the shape of the formed jets are asymmetric. These are all problems caused by the directionality of multiple pressures. The situation can be approximated as described elsewhere[38,52–57] partly. Here, we ignore the little angular shift due to the screen effect and symmetry. The interaction between the bubbles can be simplified as the interaction between bubbles and their acoustic radiation When the bubble is a spherical one, the time-varying sound pressure of its far-field can be expressed as follows:</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>p</mi><mi>a</mi></msub><mo>(</mo><mi>r</mi><mo separator="true">,</mo><mi>t</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>ρ</mi><mi>L</mi></msub><mrow><mn>4</mn><mi>π</mi><mi>r</mi></mrow></mfrac><mfrac><mrow><msup><mi>d</mi><mn>2</mn></msup><mi>V</mi></mrow><mrow><mi>d</mi><msup><mi>t</mi><mn>2</mn></msup></mrow></mfrac></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">p _ { a } ( r , t ) = \frac { \rho _ { L } } { 4 \pi r } \frac { d ^ { 2 } V } { d t ^ { 2 } }</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.151392em;"><span style="top:-2.5500000000000003em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.15em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mpunct">,</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault">t</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.36292em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">4</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.03588em;">π</span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.3448em;"><span style="top:-2.3567071428571427em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">L</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.14329285714285717em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:1.01792em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">t</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7463142857142857em;"><span style="top:-2.786em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.394em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">d</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8913142857142857em;"><span style="top:-2.931em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.22222em;">V</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span></span></span></span>(1.6)</p>
<p>where pa refers to the sound pressure of the far-field radiation, r refers to the distance from the center of the bubble to the measuring point, ρL refers to the liquid density, and V(t) represents the time-varying volume of the bubble[49]. After determining the measuring position and the relative direction of the bubble, it is reasonable to extend this formula to the radiation acoustic pressure of non-spherical bubbles based on the change of the bubble radius in one direction[58], which is</p>
<p><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><msub><mi>p</mi><mi>a</mi></msub><mo>(</mo><mi>R</mi><mo separator="true">,</mo><mi>r</mi><mo separator="true">,</mo><mi>t</mi><mo>)</mo><mo>=</mo><mfrac><msub><mi>ρ</mi><mi>L</mi></msub><mi>r</mi></mfrac><mo>⋅</mo><mi>R</mi><mo>⋅</mo><mo>(</mo><mn>2</mn><msup><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>˙</mo></mover><mn>2</mn></msup><mo>+</mo><mi>R</mi><mover accent="true"><mi>R</mi><mo>¨</mo></mover><mo>)</mo></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex">p _ { a } ( R , r , t ) = \frac { \rho _ { L } } { r } \cdot R \cdot ( 2 \dot { R } ^ { 2 } + R \ddot { R } )</annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault">p</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.151392em;"><span style="top:-2.5500000000000003em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">a</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.15em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mpunct">,</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span><span class="mpunct">,</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.16666666666666666em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault">t</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.0925em;vertical-align:-0.345em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mopen nulldelimiter"></span><span class="mfrac"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.7475em;"><span style="top:-2.6550000000000002em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight" style="margin-right:0.02778em;">r</span></span></span></span><span style="top:-3.23em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="frac-line" style="border-bottom-width:0.04em;"></span></span><span style="top:-3.446108em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">ρ</span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t vlist-t2"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.3448em;"><span style="top:-2.3567071428571427em;margin-left:0em;margin-right:0.07142857142857144em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.5em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size3 size1 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mathdefault mtight">L</span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.14329285714285717em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="vlist-s">​</span></span><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.345em;"><span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose nulldelimiter"></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">⋅</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.68333em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">⋅</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.17019em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">2</span><span class="mord"><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.055550000000000016em;">˙</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="msupsub"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.8141079999999999em;"><span style="top:-3.063em;margin-right:0.05em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:2.7em;"></span><span class="sizing reset-size6 size3 mtight"><span class="mord mtight"><span class="mord mtight">2</span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">+</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1.17019em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span><span class="mord accent"><span class="vlist-t"><span class="vlist-r"><span class="vlist" style="height:0.9201900000000001em;"><span style="top:-3em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="mord"><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.00773em;">R</span></span></span><span style="top:-3.25233em;"><span class="pstrut" style="height:3em;"></span><span class="accent-body" style="left:-0.16666em;">¨</span></span></span></span></span></span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span></span>(1.7)</p>
<p>where R(t) refers to the change of bubble radius along the direction of r. By substituting this sound pressure to the external acoustic pressure term p(t) in the K-M model, the pulsation of the bubbles affected by the far-field sound pressure can be obtained. The dimensional situation studied in this paper cannot be completely expressed by the far-field pressure. When being affected, the bubbles will lose their sphere, while their boundary and the pressure of the outward radiation will change. However, it is still quite reasonable to explain the effects suffered by bubbles using sound pressure [41]. In this regard, we can simply divide the affected bubble radiation pressure into three processes. See attached Figure 23 from the literature [51]: stage a. high-pressure pulses and constantly decreased positive pressures in the initial expansion phase; stage b. negative pressure in the stable phase; and stage c. positive pressure and high-pressure pulses formed at the end of the shrinkage. As mentioned earlier, the stage a may slow down the expansion of bubbles. Moreover, the center bubble is affected by multiple stage as and becomes slower. The stage b increases the expansion, blocks the shrinkage and causes the stretching of the bubbles, which maintain a large radius in the direction of the force for more time. The stage c accelerates the collapse or decelerate the rebound of adjacent bubbles. Since the affected collapse is directional, the results of the mentioned cases are also different. For example, in Case 1 - 2, the pressure of the verge bubble on the center bubble almost cancels out the deformation caused by stage b, while the center bubble does inhibit the rebound of the verge bubbles. In Case3 - 4, the shrinkage of the center bubble is primarily reflected in the horizontal direction. Thus, the pressure wave of center bubble formed in stage b and stage c is mainly transmitted in the horizontal direction. It is difficult to influence the verge bubbles. The effect of the verge bubbles on the center bubble is reflected in the flattening of the opposite surfaces and accelerated contraction. In Case 5, due to its proximity and phase synchronization, the three bubbles can be considered as a whole, and thus the effects of stage c can be ignored.</p>
<p>The pressure waves associated with the above three stages modify the distribution of internal and external pressure of adjacent bubbles, instead of uniform pressure difference as isolated spherical bubbles. The internal and external pressure distribution of the bubbles is determined by direction, which makes the oscillation of the bubbles in different directions show a large difference. Thus, we can assume that the radius change in different directions within a bubble has different periods, that is, a bubble has different time phases in different directions. In a bubble, the phase is delayed, where it is affected by pressure waves. For instance, where the external pressure is higher, the phase is highly delayed. The direction with the later phase reaches the maximum radius later as well as the minimum radius, namely collapse. As a result, deformation will occur. The part with the advance phase reaches the maximum, while the other one with the later phase does not reach the maximum. Then the advance phase part begins to shrink, whereas the part with the later phase has just reached its maximum. This process is often accompanied by the transposition of the bubble long axis. When the advance phase part starts to shrink sharply, the delayed phase part just starts to shrink. Therefore, forming specific deformation, for example, jets from the advance phase part to the delayed part.</p>
<p>In this work, the center bubble experienced more pressure than the verge bubbles. In addition, the ensemble phase of the center bubble was delayed more compared to that of verge bubbles. Hence, the lifetime of a center bubble is longer, the radius smaller than verge bubbles. When one specifically analyzes the individual bubble, the center bubble is first affected by the pressure wave along the vertical direction. Thus the phase delay decreases as the distance from the opposite surface to a certain position vertically increases. The central part is affected later; the phase is in advance. Therefore, as described earlier, the axis transposition, special cylindrical shape, and special forms of collapse will form. Moreover, the opposite position of the verge bubbles to the center bubble is first affected by the pressure wave, and thus its phase is later. On the other hand, the backside position in the verge bubbles is later affected by the pressure wave, and thus the phase is in advance. As a result, the oscillation of the leeward boundary in the verge bubbles precedes the windward boundary. The leeward boundary shrinks violently while the windward boundary is in the stable stage. Then the inward jet is formed on the leeward boundary. The verge bubbles in different cases form jets at different times, due to their different time phase difference between their anterior and posterior surfaces.</p>
<p>This method of dividing the interior of bubbles into different phases can be extended to the bubble arrays. Each bubble in the array can be treated as a part of the bubble described above. As noted in the literature [59], since the corner bubbles are further away from the geometric center, it can be treated as the expanded parts with advanced phase in a single bubble by analogy. Hence collapse starts from an angle rather than the edge. This perhaps may be another way to understand the direction of the collapse except for curvature.</p>
<p>Geometrically, for the R, we define based on shadow, and for a volume given bubble, the spherical bubble has the smallest max(R). Furthermore, the max(R) might become larger when bubbles lose their sphericity in deformation. In the interaction of the multiple bubbles, if the volume of the bubble does not change, the max(R) should be larger. However, each of the max(R) we measured was becoming smaller, which suggests that the volume of the bubbles affected by the interaction did not reach the maximum volume that the isolated bubbles can reach.</p>
<p>The process of bubble expansion can be regarded as a process of kinetic energy transformed into potential energy. When the internal pressure of a bubble is greater than the external pressure, it is therefore the difference between the internal and external pressure that drives work to achieve the transformation. After exceeding the equilibrium radius, the internal pressure of the bubble is less than the external pressure. The bubble transforms the residual kinetic energy into potential energy through inertia. When multiple bubbles interact, the bubble energy is not only transformed from kinetic energy to potential energy but also a part of the kinetic energy transfer that makes the bubble position move relatively. During expansion, there is a push effect in bubbles that keeps adjacent bubbles away from themselves. When bubbles are far away, the multi-bubble system accumulates potential energy. During shrinkage, the potential energy of the bubble system is transformed into kinetic energy, including the kinetic energy of bubble shrinkage as well as the bubble movement. This process is a unified process relevant to the equilibrium radius. However, since the driving force of the two transformations in this process is not the same one, they have some independence. Thus, the time of the maximum bubble radius and the maximum distance do not coincide.</p>
<p>Without the consideration of the change of deformation to R, max(R) is directly used to calculate the bubble energy E= (4/3)π(max(R))3p0. The normalized bubble energy  is obtained by comparing it to E0, using R0 in the energy equation.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th>γ=0.45</th>
<th>γ=0.80</th>
<th>γ=1.0</th>
<th>γ=1.47</th>
<th>γ=1.93</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Center bubble</td>
<td>0.7360</td>
<td>0.7584</td>
<td>0.7895</td>
<td>0.7833</td>
<td>0.8507</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Verge bubbles</td>
<td>0.7115</td>
<td>0.7216</td>
<td>0.7502</td>
<td>0.7994</td>
<td>0.8702</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Sum</td>
<td>2.1590</td>
<td>2.2015</td>
<td>2.2898</td>
<td>2.3820</td>
<td>2.5911</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Tablet 1. Normalized bubble energy</p>
<p>In the table above, the maximum 20 values for each set of R are averaged and then calculate  . The Sum column is the result of one center bubble plus two verge bubbles. It can be noted that as γ decreases, the bubble energy contained in bubbles with maximum radius is declining. This implies that the bubble energy transformed into the bubble potential energy is increasing, which is consistent with our results of the pushing distance  .</p>
<h1 id="v-conclusion">V. Conclusion</h1>
<p>In this work, the dynamics of three uniformly separated laser-induced bubbles were experimentally studied. The precise control of distance and energy achieves the multi-bubbles interaction in one life period under ideal conditions. As a parameter of evenly distributed multi-cavitation space, γ is the main parameter in this study. The study shows:</p>
<ol>
<li>In bubble arrays, the lifetime of each bubble is generally extended, while the volume is reduced. This phenomenon is most apparent for the center bubble because of the most inhibition it received. In shrinkage, the lifetime difference causes the collapse of bubbles to proceed in an orderly manner, from the outside to the inside. Meanwhile, the smaller the γ, the more evident is this phenomenon.</li>
<li>The different phase delay in different parts of a bubble causes the unique shape of bubbles. From a relatively independent perspective, it can be considered that for the inner part of a bubble, the closer it is to the adjacent bubble, the more the phase delay. This phenomenon is achieved through the interaction between the bubbles and the acoustic radiation of the cavitation pulsation. The acoustic radiation changes the pressure difference between the interior and exterior of bubbles, which has an inhibitory effect on the continuous motion at the corresponding pulsation phase, thus delaying the phase of bubble parts.</li>
<li>In the three-bubble system with the same initial phase and equal spacing, there are various forms of the collapse of the center bubble: normal collapse; slightly elongated in the direction of alignment; elongating to a long stick; necking to an hourglass. When the γ is sufficiently small, the compression effect is more efficacious than stretching, then the center bubble was compacted to a dish. The center bubbles do not produce jets, while the verge bubbles produce jets towards the center, and the jets become stronger as the γ decreases. The beginning of the loss of circularity, which generally indicates the stability of the shape of bubbles, can occur at any stage. It moves forward as the γ decreases, from the end of shrinkage to the beginning of bubbles.</li>
<li>During the oscillation of the bubble array, the bubbles interact with each other through acoustic radiation, and the energy transfer changes the relative position of the bubbles. In expansion, the verge bubbles are pushed outward, while in shrinkage, they are pulled inward. The smaller the γ, the more apparent is the phenomenon.<br>
The interaction of multiple cavitation bubbles is discussed in this paper. The parameters R, A, B, C, and D are used to describe the interaction. However, further parameters describing the deformation during the interaction are needed especially in future research. Also, the lifetime extensions require to be quantified. The fate of the cavitation energy needs more accurate measurements. Whilst, the experimental method should be improved to obtain more accurate information about the bubbles in interaction. Therefore, further improvement should focus on the multiple bubbles dynamics in more detailed cases of parameter γ &lt; 1. Of note, this research provides valuable information for further understanding of the mechanism of multiple cavitation bubbles in medical and hydraulic engineering.</li>
</ol>
<h1 id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</h1>
<p>This research was supported by the National Natural Science Foundation of China (No.11774176).</p>
<h1 id="references">References</h1>
<p>[1]	N. Ochiai, J. Ishimoto, Numerical analysis of the effect of bubble distribution on multiple-bubble behavior, Ultrason. Sonochem. 61 (2020) 104818. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2019.104818.<br>
[2]	R. Timm, Optical and acoustic investigations of the dynamics of laser-produced cavitation bubbles near a solid boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 206 (1989) 299–338. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112089002314.<br>
[3]	S. LI, Cavitation enhancement of silt erosion—An envisaged micro model, Wear. 260 (2006) 1145–1150. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.WEAR.2005.07.002.<br>
[4]	W. Lauterborn, H. Bolle, Experimental investigations of cavitation-bubble collapse in the neighbourhood of a solid boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 72 (1975) 391–399. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112075003448.<br>
[5]	P. Cui, A.-M.M. Zhang, S. Wang, B.C. Khoo, Ice breaking by a collapsing bubble, J. Fluid Mech. 841 (2018) 287–309. https://doi.org/10.1017/jfm.2018.63.<br>
[6]	N. Vyas, Q.X. Wang, K.A. Manmi, R.L. Sammons, S.A. Kuehne, A.D. Walmsley, How does ultrasonic cavitation remove dental bacterial biofilm?, Ultrason. Sonochem. 67 (2020) 105112. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2020.105112.<br>
[7]	C. Ohl, T. Kurz, R. Geisler, O. Lindau, W. Lauterborn, Bubble dynamics, shock waves and sonoluminescence, Philos. Trans. R. Soc. London. Ser. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci. 357 (1999) 269–294. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsta.1999.0327.<br>
[8]	P.M. Kanthale, P.R. Gogate, A.B. Pandit, A. Marie Wilhelm, Cavity cluster approach for quantification of cavitational intensity in sonochemical reactors, Ultrason. Sonochem. 10 (2003) 181–189. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1350-4177(03)00088-9.<br>
[9]	F. Reuter, S. Lesnik, K. Ayaz-Bustami, G. Brenner, R. Mettin, Bubble size measurements in different acoustic cavitation structures: Filaments, clusters, and the acoustically cavitated jet, Ultrason. Sonochem. 55 (2019) 383–394. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2018.05.003.<br>
[10]	D.H. Peregrine, The Acoustic Bubble. By T. G. Leighton. Academic Press, 1994. 613 pp. 95. ISBN 0-12-441920-8., J. Fluid Mech. 272 (1994) 407–408. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112094214519.<br>
[11]	Lord Rayleigh, VIII. On the pressure developed in a liquid during the collapse of a spherical cavity, London, Edinburgh, Dublin Philos. Mag. J. Sci. 34 (1917) 94–98. https://doi.org/10.1080/14786440808635681.<br>
[12]	W. Lauterborn, C.D. Ohl, Cavitation bubble dynamics, Ultrason. Sonochem. (1997). https://doi.org/10.1016/S1350-4177(97)00009-6.<br>
[13]	M. Reiner, On volume-or isotropic flow as exemplified in the creep of concrete, Flow, Turbul. Combust. 1 (1949) 475.<br>
[14]	E.A. Brujan, K. Nahen, P. Schmidt, A. Vogel, Dynamics of laser-induced cavitation bubbles near an elastic boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 433 (2001) 251–281. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112000003347.<br>
[15]	D. Obreschkow, P. Kobel, N. Dorsaz, A. De Bosset, C. Nicollier, M. Farhat, Cavitation bubble dynamics inside liquid drops in microgravity, Phys. Rev. Lett. (2006). https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.97.094502.<br>
[16]	S. Poulain, G. Guenoun, S. Gart, W. Crowe, S. Jung, Particle Motion Induced by Bubble Cavitation, Phys. Rev. Lett. 114 (2015) 214501. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.114.214501.<br>
[17]	J.B. Keller, M. Miksis, Bubble oscillations of large amplitude, J. Acoust. Soc. Am. 68 (1980) 628–633. https://doi.org/10.1121/1.384720.<br>
[18]	W. Lauterborn, T. Kurz, Physics of bubble oscillations, Reports Prog. Phys. 73 (2010) 106501. https://doi.org/10.1088/0034-4885/73/10/106501.<br>
[19]	J.R. Blake, G.S. Keen, R.P. Tong, M. Wilson, Acoustic cavitation: The fluid dynamics of non-spherical bubbles, Philos. Trans. R. Soc. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci. 357 (1999) 251–267. https://doi.org/10.1098/rsta.1999.0326.<br>
[20]	A. Biesheuvel, L. V. Wijngaarden, Two-phase flow equations for a dilute dispersion of gas bubbles in liquid, J. Fluid Mech. 148 (1984) 301–318. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112084002366.<br>
[21]	D.Z. Zhang, A. Prosperetti, Ensemble phase-averaged equations for bubbly flows, Phys. Fluids. 6 (1994) 2956–2970. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.868122.<br>
[22]	D. Fuster, T. Colonius, Modelling bubble clusters in compressible liquids, J. Fluid Mech. 688 (2011) 352–389. https://doi.org/10.1017/jfm.2011.380.<br>
[23]	M. Arora, C.D. Ohl, D. Lohse, Effect of nuclei concentration on cavitation cluster dynamics, J. Acoust. Soc. Am. 121 (2007) 3432. https://doi.org/10.1121/1.2722045.<br>
[24]	G. Servant, J.L. Laborde, A. Hita, J.P. Caltagirone, A. Gérard, On the interaction between ultrasound waves and bubble clouds in mono- and dual-frequency sonoreactors, Ultrason. Sonochem. 10 (2003) 347–355. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1350-4177(03)00105-6.<br>
[25]	E. Johnsen, T. Colonius, Shock-induced collapse of a gas bubble in shockwave lithotripsy, J. Acoust. Soc. Am. 124 (2008) 2011–2020. https://doi.org/10.1121/1.2973229.<br>
[26]	M.R. Betney, B. Tully, N.A. Hawker, Y. Ventikos, Computational modelling of the interaction of shock waves with multiple gas-filled bubbles in a liquid, Phys. Fluids. 27 (2015) 1–28. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.4914133.<br>
[27]	W. Lauterborn, T. Kurz, R. Geisler, D. Schanz, O. Lindau, Acoustic cavitation, bubble dynamics and sonoluminescence, Ultrason. Sonochem. 14 (2007) 484–491. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2006.09.017.<br>
[28]	A. Shima, The Natural Frequencies of Two Spherical Bubbles Oscillating in Water, J. Basic Eng. 93 (1971) 426–431. https://doi.org/10.1115/1.3425268.<br>
[29]	H.N. Oguz, A. Prosperetti, A generalization of the impulse and virial theorems with an application to bubble oscillations, J. Fluid Mech. 218 (1990) 143. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112090000957.<br>
[30]	R. Mettin, I. Akhatov, U. Parlitz, C.D. Ohl, W. Lauterborn, Bjerknes forces between small cavitation bubbles in a strong acoustic field, Phys. Rev. E. 56 (1997) 2924–2931. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.56.2924.<br>
[31]	A. HARKIN, T.J. KAPER, A.L.I. NADIM, Coupled pulsation and translation of two gas bubbles in a liquid, J. Fluid Mech. 445 (2001) 377–411. https://doi.org/10.1017/s0022112001005857.<br>
[32]	A. Shima, T. Fujiwara, The behavior of two bubbles near a solid wall, Arch. Appl. Mech. 62 (1992) 53–61. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00786681.<br>
[33]	B. Han, K. Köhler, K. Jungnickel, R. Mettin, W. Lauterborn, A. Vogel, Dynamics of laser-induced bubble pairs, J. Fluid Mech. 771 (2015) 706–742. https://doi.org/10.1017/jfm.2015.183.<br>
[34]	S.W. Fong, D. Adhikari, E. Klaseboer, B.C. Khoo, Interactions of multiple spark-generated bubbles with phase differences, Exp. Fluids. 46 (2009) 705–724. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00348-008-0603-4.<br>
[35]	P.A. Quinto-Su, C.D. Ohl, Interaction between two laser-induced cavitation bubbles in a quasi-two-dimensional geometry, J. Fluid Mech. 633 (2009) 425–435. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112009008064.<br>
[36]	P. Cui, Q.X. Wang, S.P. Wang, A.M. Zhang, Experimental study on interaction and coalescence of synchronized multiple bubbles, Phys. Fluids. 28 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1063/1.4939007.<br>
[37]	W. Lauterborn, T. Kurz, R. Mettin, C.D. Ohl, Experimental and Theoretical Bubble Dynamics, 2007. https://doi.org/10.1002/9780470141694.ch5.<br>
[38]	H. Chen, Z. Chen, Y. Li, Modulation of the secondary Bjerknes force in multi-bubble systems, Ultrason. Sonochem. 61 (2020) 104814. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2019.104814.<br>
[39]	J.P. Dear, J.E. Field, A.J. Walton, Gas compression and jet formation in cavities collapsed by a shock wave, Nature. 332 (1988) 505–508. https://doi.org/10.1038/332505a0.<br>
[40]	J.P. Dear, J.E. Field, A study of the collapse of arrays of cavities, J. Fluid Mech. 190 (1988) 409–425. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112088001387.<br>
[41]	N. Bremond, M. Arora, S.M. Dammer, D. Lohse, Interaction of cavitation bubbles on a wall, Phys. Fluids. 18 (2006) 121505. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.2396922.<br>
[42]	N. Bremond, M. Arora, C.D. Ohl, D. Lohse, Controlled multibubble surface cavitation, Phys. Rev. Lett. 96 (2006) 1–4. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.224501.<br>
[43]	E. Lauer, X.Y. Hu, S. Hickel, N.A. Adams, Numerical investigation of collapsing cavity arrays, Phys. Fluids. 24 (2012). https://doi.org/10.1063/1.4719142.<br>
[44]	L.W. Chew, E. Klaseboer, S.W. Ohl, B.C. Khoo, Interaction of two differently sized oscillating bubbles in a free field, Phys. Rev. E - Stat. Nonlinear, Soft Matter Phys. 84 (2011) 1–11. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.84.066307.<br>
[45]	S. Hysing, S. Turek, D. Kuzmin, N. Parolini, E. Burman, S. Ganesan, L. Tobiska, Quantitative benchmark computations of two-dimensional bubble dynamics, Int. J. Numer. Methods Fluids. 60 (2009) 1259–1288. https://doi.org/10.1002/fld.1934.<br>
[46]	D. Kröninger, K. Köhler, T. Kurz, W. Lauterborn, Particle tracking velocimetry of the flow field around a collapsing cavitation bubble, Exp. Fluids. 48 (2010) 395–408. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00348-009-0743-1.<br>
[47]	C. Zhang, J. Lu, H. Zhang, Z. Shen, X. Ni, Transient Coupling Model of Plasma and Laser Field in Water, IEEE J. Quantum Electron. 52 (2016). https://doi.org/10.1109/JQE.2016.2588465.<br>
[48]	W. Lauterborn, A. Vogel, Shock wave emission by laser generated bubbles, 2013. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-34297-4_3.<br>
[49]	C.E. Brennen, Cavitation and bubble dynamics, Cambridge University Press, 2013. https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781107338760.<br>
[50]	C.D. Ohl, S.W. Ohl, ShockWave interaction with single bubbles and bubble clouds, in: Bubble Dyn. Shock Waves, Springer Berlin Heidelberg, 2013: pp. 3–31. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-642-34297-4_1.<br>
[51]	L. Lv, Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, Experimental investigations of the particle motions induced by a laser-generated cavitation bubble, Ultrason. Sonochem. 56 (2019) 63–76. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2019.03.019.<br>
[52]	B. Han, J. Chen, Z.H. Shen, J. Lu, X.W. Ni, Investigation of the wedge-shaped propelled surface for laser propulsion in water environment, Opt. Laser Technol. 43 (2011) 604–608. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.optlastec.2010.08.008.<br>
[53]	E.A. Brujan, H. Takahira, T. Ogasawara, Planar jets in collapsing cavitation bubbles, Exp. Therm. Fluid Sci. 101 (2019) 48–61. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.expthermflusci.2018.10.007.<br>
[54]	E.A. Brujan, Y. Matsumoto, Shock wave emission from a hemispherical cloud of bubbles in non-Newtonian fluids, J. Nonnewton. Fluid Mech. 204 (2014) 32–37. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jnnfm.2013.12.003.<br>
[55]	Y. Tomita, P.B. Robinson, R.P. Tong, J.R. Blake, Growth and collapse of cavitation bubbles near a curved rigid boundary, J. Fluid Mech. 466 (2002) 259–283. https://doi.org/10.1017/S0022112002001209.<br>
[56]	F.I. Azam, B. Karri, S.-W. Ohl, E. Klaseboer, B.C. Khoo, Dynamics of an oscillating bubble in a narrow gap, Phys. Rev. E. 88 (2013) 043006. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.88.043006.<br>
[57]	P.A. Quinto-Su, K.Y. Lim, C.D. Ohl, Cavitation bubble dynamics in microfluidic gaps of variable height, Phys. Rev. E - Stat. Nonlinear, Soft Matter Phys. 80 (2009) 047301. https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevE.80.047301.<br>
[58]	Y. Zhang, Y. Zhang, S. Li, The secondary Bjerknes force between two gas bubbles under dual-frequency acoustic excitation, Ultrason. Sonochem. 29 (2016) 129–145. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ultsonch.2015.08.022.<br>
[59]	P.A. Quinto-Su, C.-D.D. Ohl, Bubble cluster explosion, Phys. Fluids. 22 (2010) 091109. https://doi.org/10.1063/1.3483221.</p>
<!-- more -->
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[A busy day ]]></title>
        <id>https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/a-busy-day/</id>
        <link href="https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/a-busy-day/">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-12-30T13:27:08.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!-- more -->
<!-- more -->
<p>WORK AND EAT</p>
<!-- more -->
<!-- more -->
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[About]]></title>
        <id>https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/about/</id>
        <link href="https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/about/">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-12-21T17:25:23.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://hengzhubao.github.io//post-images/1576949215016.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy"><br>
Prof. Qian<br>
I don't know how would he judge me, what would he tell me.</p>
<p>I singing</p>
<p>I'm just trying to fill my empty brain with something intresting!</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[关于本科前教师的一些回忆]]></title>
        <id>https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/shide/</id>
        <link href="https://hengzhubao.github.io/post/shide/">
        </link>
        <updated>2019-04-04T12:23:10.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="啰嗦了一堆趣事和让人心情不好的事而不做政治分析-大家不要介意">啰嗦了一堆趣事和让人心情不好的事，而不做政治分析。大家不要介意</h2>
<p>全文无图，约5500字。<br>
今天跟朋友说起博士毕业后的职业规划，我坚定的想成为一个人民教师。于是我不得不回忆起我在孩提时代作为一个既学习好又爱玩的学生所遭受的各种痛苦经历，以此来对教师队伍的世俗性进行批判，并对我想成为一个人民教师给学生展示美和高尚的志向进行合理性解释。<br>
我进入小学时是世纪之交的99年，村里还是一个较为淳朴封闭的环境。那个时候的梦想是成为一名小混混，成为镇上初中“十三太保”、“四大金刚”中的一员。但是奈何家长比较重视教育，一年级期中考试还一不小心拿了六优第一，就让我这个心理不太安分的小学生受到了学校和家中的特别关注。村里老师多数是民办老师，有的还沾亲带故的，甚至父子两代人都是跟着一个老师读的比比皆是。老师的绝对权威不容质疑。一年级时最开始的班长是班主任门口的小孩。他带领村北的同学们把我打了，但广大同学们的眼睛是雪亮的，在班里几乎所有同学的一致指证下，他由于打我还撒谎下台了，而我则因为挨揍还诚实荣登班长，整个过程就是儿戏。有一次，三年级的班主任让我们自习，身为班干部的我就主动的维持纪律。但在下一堂课，老师问谁下位了，我想到我到讲台上也算是下位了吧，就站了起来。然后老师用他们成人的想法，直接没问问题就把我打了一顿。真真是百口莫辩。我的伯父在我小学时还在世，因为离婚分割财产的问题，跟他的几个大舅哥闹得很僵。而恰恰他二舅哥的老婆就是我五年级的班主任。当我听到班主任在班里教育同学们理我远一点的时候，我也是很不解。每当参与到小伙伴的活动时，总用那么几个人会放声：老师不让咱们跟他玩！心中有百般的委屈和无奈。我父亲也曾问过这个班主任对我好不好，但是出于那么一点小大人的自尊和对自己在学校的不足的愧疚，终究是没跟父亲如实道来。我在还是个孩子时，总是觉得自己做的不好做的还可以提高，做的像是给家里人丢脸，总是不把学校的事情告诉家长。这也使得我接下来在学校遭受的种种不好，都没有被家长知晓并及时制止。<br>
我们那里试验小学五年初中四年的五四制，试验了几十年，所以我五年级毕业就升入初中读六年级了。六年级又是一次期中考试，忽然就成了年级第二，班里第一。忽然就受到了各路老师的关注。有点可恨的是，本来以为是个调皮的孩子结果是个聪明孩子这个事实接受不能的语文老师，忽然就开始对我严厉起来了，甚至是变态的严厉了，插句话，初中语文老师是最严厉的老师，高中的语文老师是最宽松的老师。上课不能交头接耳，不能坐姿不端，必须忍受她对着我喷幽门螺旋杆菌。略加质疑就动辄则咎。最后实在忍不了，就变回了以前活泼的孩子。然后，那个女老师，我至今记得名字的王八蛋，就把我从六年级教室拎到了七年级，让我趴在七年级六班进入教室的台阶上，看那本我小学无聊时就看了几遍的语文书，以图折损我那孩子的自尊，和在班里的小小的号召力。这也的确做到了，至今是一个笑谈，我没敢反抗她，因为我觉得在学校没有好好学习本身就是有错的，有错就没有权利去博得同情。但是这么多年过去了，我仍然神恨着她，一个用折损学生自尊的方法来建立老师威信的魔鬼，一个口中喷粪的恶毒女人。最后幸亏是一个满校园游荡种树的校长或者副校长看到了，才终结了这痛苦的一个多周的羞辱。<br>
因为成绩优异在升七年级时，被刚开创但打不开局面的某私立中学看中，让我免学费学杂费就读他们学校。然后我就很开心的逃离了给我羞辱的乡下初中。一开始招生的那个大学生数学老师——戴老师特别温暖，我很喜欢她，她也是我的班主任。但后来因学校极速扩大，在省内贫困地区挖了好多教学名师，让他们来推行他们的先进经验。然后我的班主任就换成了一个光明顶的语文老师。每天六点起，上课上自习知道晚上九点。我的妈啊，我这么活泼的一个孩子怎么受得了？做作业也快，又不愿意自习，成绩还好，上课闲着没事就修修计算器，看看窗外，大开一些脑洞。也不影响其他人，毕竟他们都像是机器人一样，连头都不敢抬，根本玩不到一处。戴老师当班主任时还能经常出个小难题，让我解一下。等语文班主任上岗后，就开始让我补语文短板。阅读理解，背，抄。最后还是因为上课抬头批评我，我还嘴了，而把我送到了政教处。那个画着刻薄眉毛的中年妇女抓着我就是一顿教育，也不容我回嘴，最后还在周一的升国旗仪式上当着全校同学的面点名批评七年级六班有个我不老实，竟然敢上自习抬头，老师教育时还顶撞老师。竟然同学们都很认同！大家都低头，都服从老师，为啥就你抬头乱看，为啥就你跟老师讲道理？虽然周围都是套子里的人，但我喜欢这个学校，因为这个学校当时的条件在现在看来都很现代化，我喜欢这种物质上的满足感。但又是某个沾亲带故的原来的初中老师，半年到我家不知多少次，天天来混饭混茶来磨我父亲，求我回原来的初中，然后用我当典型来及时制止那股人才流失之风。然后我父亲就在他私立学校即将覆灭的危言耸听和各种许诺的甜言蜜语中让我回到了原来的初中。我也是自无不可，回原来的初中，不看权，不看势，我还能继续当小头头。可是谁知，由于跟我同批出走的没有回去的，只有我回来了，在老师眼中就变成了我在彼处混不好，灰溜溜的回来了。于是各路老师就开了嘲讽技能，闲着没事就给我点人生经验。其中语文老师，一个肥胖的天天画着烟熏妆的刻薄老女人最是为甚。八年级也是跟着她读，可被她给打惨了，打得我在同学中成为笑柄。阅读理解跟她读的差一个字就是一顿打，然后就练就了我对着老师没脸没皮哀求的能力。七年级下学期的生物老师是个肥胖的中年男人，不知有什么病，上课天天带着手绢擦汗，甚至在厕所晕倒过。脑袋也有点问题，经常莫名其妙的发脾气打人，跟一个叫做丰荣的学生简直是天生父子，俩人十分能怼得开。就这么一个老师，曾经上课讲到兴头处忽然间把我叫到讲台上，让我蹲下，然后在门后大竹条扫帚上抽取一根细竹，对着我就是一顿猛抽。一开始把我打蒙了，我都没做任何事就挨了揍呢，我反应过来就跑出教室。然后就上演了一出你回来，我不打你的骗局。最后竟然是僵持到下课，他看见丰荣，去打他了，才结束这荒诞的一幕。他有病，我理解，我同情。但是有精神病仍然放在学校里祸害学生，是真不能理解了。<br>
有脑残的老师还有很多，接下来我会遇到更多。<br>
升八年级时，因为个人出了一点事故，差点丢了命，做了开颅手术，住院住到开学快俩月。在没回学校时，就听我发小说，化学老师是个傻叉。上一节课是体育课，同学们有很多会去买个冰块，解解渴降降温。然后这节课有两个同学买冰块踩着铃声进了教室。这个化学老师，暂时称之为大牙吧，就让这俩同学把冰块放在讲台上。上课一字一顿的讲着化学实验的操作步骤，还偷偷的在冰块袋子里拿取冰块吃。最可笑的是，被冻的捂着嘴嗷嗷叫，还要继续吃。到下课时，走到那俩同学面前问人家：下次还敢不敢迟到了？真是滑天下之大稽！我回学校不久我就体会到了。因为我回来的晚，又学习好，那个喊我回来的亲戚老师还特意照顾，我就坐在第一排。有一天，我趴在桌子上睡觉，朦朦胧胧感到后面的同学在踢我，然后醒转过来，我就问咋啦？后面的女同学告诉我大牙叫我。然后我就懵逼的看着大牙说：咋啦老师？他回我：别和xxx（我后排的同学）说话！我在中学阶段可是傲娇的很，男生可以无所谓，女生我可是要看人的，大多数我都是一句话都不跟他们说的，而后排俩，恰恰属于我根本不会主动搭话的女生。我一听这话甚是惊讶：老师，我没说话啊！大牙神回路的说：你还说！我更是惊诧万分了，这是什么逻辑：老师我真没说啊！大牙回道：你还敢说，你给我滚出去！我也是要脸要皮的带头大哥级人物，出去就出去呗，没说话就是没说话，懒得看这种嘴脸。课上完了，我的傻叉班主任上场了。这老哥九年级不教我了后，天天朝我索贿，朝我要东西，因为八年级吃海参吃上瘾了嘛，天天喊着让我送海参，就像不怕全校人知道他吃过我爸送的海参一样。这位唇彩班主任一听大牙说我上课说话还顶撞老师，就踢我打我的让我叫家长，我没做当然要坦荡荡的死不承认啦。然后从办公桌后面抽出铁棍一根，瞄准我，说要打死我个王八蛋。而大牙主动抱住他说要让我自己承认。办公室其他老师都过来让我承认错误道个歉叫个家长就算了，我一一的回到：没说就是没说，打死我，我也没说。最后办公室就剩了这俩蠢材和我，由于是上午最后一节发生的刚才所述一幕，午饭都没吃，争吵了一整个午睡的时间。我气的浑身发抖，双腿发颤，我永远忘不了那种感觉。一个老师诬陷我，一个老师草爹爹进妈妈的要干死我，而我只能在那忍受他们的暴力，梗着脖子讲着我没说就是没说。至今想想甚是可笑，什么样子的小丑都想做到学生的头上作威作福，拉屎撒尿。我虽然被现实多次教育过了，可因为没有一个主心骨，一个合理解决这种事情的哲学思想指导，到了都没有敢打倒这群反动派。<br>
到九年级，我遇到了更加逗比的老师。<br>
我们那一带有一个精神有问题的流浪汉，最后死在了山洞里，大家都叫他谭店。然后这位谭店有一个侄女，九年级时跟我同班。我那逗比的班主任上课以“谭店起来回答问题”、“谭店，你妈个臭逼的”取乐，人品实在是差。因我学习好，而且有较多精力，把每天打扫卫生的活就交给我和另外两位学习无望的同学。每天早上人家在上早自习，我拿着大竹条扫帚在土路上扫着石子，等待他过来检查。他家在校园里开辟了一个小菜园子，经常性的让我带着几个同学去维护。稍有不如意，就叫家长。每次叫来家长就是一顿礼品。然后回道也没什么事，就是最近学习不认真，我觉得有必要跟家里沟通下。就是不说到底因为什么事而把家长叫来，所以我特别烦这种不解决事，专门翻外篇前篇的人。冬天下雪，大家都在玩雪。我上完厕所回来，看见雪不错，就抓了一个球。像我这种爱抻着的人，根本就不会去打雪仗。然后这位老师就要求我团一个直径三十厘米以上的雪球，我抱着都困难那种，让我在办公室用手捧了一节课，还威胁我，不捧就让我爸把我接回家。想想也是我爸没有告诉过我绝对站在我一边，就让我心有顾虑，不敢勇敢的面对这种不平事，而他之所以没有这样说过，也怨我没有告诉他事实的真相。革命的力量要明白知道真相后才更容易爆发，藏着掖着是不能成事的。这个老师奴役学生也就算了，自己也腆着脸去贴食堂这个校内资本的屁股。每天去帮着发饭挣顿饭就不说了，就说我与食堂发生矛盾一事。食堂做饭用的菜都是那种比较坏的菜，像辣椒这种清炒的更是容易让人一眼看出来。那天排到我后，我说要西红柿，因为几乎没人吃那种一眼就能看出好坏的辣椒，剩的比较多，然后食堂大妈直接给我来了一勺辣椒。因为有插队现象，而且食堂要求先扣费，所以我的饭卡一直放在卡机上。我一看是辣椒，我就说：我不要辣椒，我要西红柿。食堂大妈一听直接给我扣费一份辣椒一份西红柿。我都蒙了，我说我只要西红柿，这个辣椒你强行摊牌给我的，我不要。大妈说都盛到钵子里去了，你就吃了吧。哎，我想吃一份西红柿就行，你摊牌给我一份辣椒，还特别恶心的用塑料袋盛了西红柿给我，这是诚心不让我吃饭，还特意坑我钱啊。我就不愿意了，我不吃了，你还我钱，我什么都不要了，没见过这么欺负人的。然后这位老师来了之后，踢了我好几脚，让我免费为食堂干了一顿活，还用开除我威胁我。开除这个威胁，直到有一次，我找了一波人先发制人以后，被叫家长吃了一顿饭后，才发现，学习好真的不会被开除，而学习不好的就不一定了。<br>
只能说这些义务教育阶段的老师用他们的亲身表演来告诉我们这些乡下学子们：社会就是这样子，社会上的坏人们都像老师一样表现着。只要别像他们一样搞，在社会上肯定能靠自己活下去。<br>
上了高中以后，高一没分班还好，因为没什么有权有势的在我们这个班，我就是风中摇曳的最吊的草。班主任一个英语老师除了爱吹牛逼爱出脑经急转弯，没啥特别的地方。一样的套路，最开始他随意指定了一个班长，学习特别差，行为特别恶劣。我就看不过眼了，主动提出让这个滚蛋，让我来！然后我就成了。他给了我最大的权限，让我去管理一个班级，而我也很乐意发挥自己过盛的精力去帮他做好这件事。后来因为开家长会，这位老师也吃请了吧，我也没特意挂念他。到了高二一开始走班，就逐渐的发现不同了。虽然我是行政班班长，但是只管自习，更重要的是学习班。然后我就发现有某些有权有钱有势的同学明明学习很差，却依然能来到我们实验班来学习。他们可以享受较高等教育，但是并不是凭真本事。我的好兄弟却因为没有任何背景，学习虽然中等但绝对比这些人好，却没办法到实验班。这是我愤愤不平之所在。他们这些既得利益者在中等教育这块都能插得上脚，是包括校领导到班主任的背叛社会主义，我根本不会给这些人好脸色看，拒绝他们给我的所有安排。高二和高三的数学老师，高二时是我班主任。因为逐渐感觉到高考的压力，我的父亲托我的一个舅伯（时任市里另一所重点高中校长）和村里大伯的亲戚（时任某教研组组长）多次宴请我校领导、班主任和语文老师，这也使得这个班主任真的是开始变本加厉的关注我。动辄叫家长，虽然我没叫，其实自己叫了。甚至有一晚喝的眼睛发红，在后门窗户里跟我对视。想想真是可笑。有一次课间，有个同学在走廊里连续两次把整个楼层的电给断了，而政教处正好在我们楼层。政教处值班老师的联众刚开就断电，搞得他恼羞成怒。而我也甚是愤怒，我在好好的学习，你给我断电，但这也激发了我的好奇心，以前从没发现还有这种事。于是我就过去看看那个开关是怎么回事。然后正好被恼怒的政教处老师看见。把我逮起来，拉到办公室看了一会他操作神奇的联众扑克，然后扣分了事。第二天，这位班主任，就不由分说的让我叫家长。我说你至少去问问班里其他同学，是谁搞的，我真是无妄之灾。就是不听，死活让我回家休息两个周，我哭得稀里哗啦不如一顿饭。xx。其他老师对教学尚算公事公办，对任何人都是无所谓，对我当然也是无所谓，也不多提，只能说他们就是一群普通人穿了老师的衣服。<br>
今天写了很长时间，头都晕了。到最后就不想写了。写的太细了没意思。在这我要郑重的感谢我高中的生物老师：刘芬红老师。她让我在学校感受到了带有母性光辉的师德，只因为是学生、是孩子而对学生好的好老师。没给她送过任何东西，家里也没有背景，之前我都没见过她，甚至我什么都没做，在走班的第一堂课就能得到她真切的关怀。直到高考失利的当晚，情绪失控到想要来年再战，也只有她一个人来安慰我让我坚定的考下去。所以我本科时每个假期都去看望她，读博以后假期变短，也大概一两年一次的去她家混顿饭吃。<br>
我初高中见过太多的杂碎老师，一副小市民心态的教育学生。根本不能让学生们心悦诚服的聚集在老师的身边，而是通过信息不对称和所谓自己神圣的权力让学生们匍伏在他们面前。他们厌恶敢于反抗他们恶治的学生，厌恶敢于思考凭什么的学生，就仿佛我们仍然生活在封建社会一般。有太多的同学不具有我这种同时身兼两个阶层的特点，没有感同身受的感受到这种变态。即使有的同学经历如我，他们也会选一个队站，而不是站在这边为另一边想。<br>
更多的老师是那种平庸的，对学生的精神世界毫不关心，而只是把他们当成机器人。完成自己的任务后，就与机器人再也无关，以后学生记得自己是幸事，不记得也怨不得别人。<br>
北大钱理群教授说：“作为一名教师，只要站在讲台上，就应该把生命中最美好的一面呈现在学生面前。使学生感受到一种精神的美。好的教育就是把学生生命中内在的最美好的东西诱发出来。教育过程就是师生相互的一个扬善抑恶的过程。”<br>
这句话我送给各位和我自己。希望我们将来不管是作为孩子的第一老师还是学校的老师都能做到扬善抑恶，把最美的一面展现给我们爱着的人。</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>